We have come to the end of the first sessions of CODESA. The results we have achieved confirm the vision contained in our statement yesterday. The foundations laid over these two days by the adoption of the Declaration of Intent and the agreement to establish working groups form the basis for a rapid movement forward. 

We are very pleased with the frank and open way in which all organisations present put forward their views. In the context I would like to make a few remarks regarding the proposals 

contained in the statement of the Government yesterday. 

The African National Congress has consistently put forward demands for a legitimate constitution-making process, including the establishment of an interim government of national unity and an elected constituent assembly to draw up and adopt a new constitution for South Africa. 

We welcome the fact that the government has acknowledged the legitimacy of various points we have raised in this regard, These include the demand that the national party should not be referee and player, that an interim government of national unity should be established expeditiously, and that both the present constitution and the tricameral parliament have no legitimacy. We also note the reference to a constituent assembly as part of the agenda for discussion. 

We are ready to consider the proposals which the government says it is almost ready to present concerning these matters. 

We must, however, make it perfectly clear that any proposals, which aim at legitimizing the tricameral parliament by restructuring it through co-option are totally unacceptable. So also are suggestions to hold racially based referenda. 

Furthermore, the idea of the establishment of an interim government which finds its form in a glorified tricameral parliament with an indefinite time span is equally unacceptable. 

We re-iterate that the central demand of the African National Congress remains the full and meaningful participation by all South Africa's people, including those in the TBVC states, in the whole process ui up and adoption of the new constitution. For us this means an elected constituent assembly. 

For the ANC it is also critical that an interim government of national unity which should be of limited duration should be established expeditiously. 

Amongst the proposals that have emerged, we would like to highlight the call for a CODESA amnesty for all remaining political prisoners before Christmas. 

We firmly believe that from what we have achieved to date we can have a new constitution in place by Christmas 1992.