<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1990-01-01">01 January 1990</date><text><term key="1129" /><body>1. The Present Perspective on the Negotiations 

A. Ongoing discussions between ANC and the government Cyril Ramaphosa and Roelf Meyer having discussions to resolve the deadlock on the situation of 

1. Political prisoners 

2. Cultural weapons 

3. Hospitals 

b. The matter of the constituent assembly and the Interim Government. Our perspective and what we need to work for in terms of elections for the C.A. 

2. Building Unity in the Face of Diversity 

A. The government has not abandoned its strategy of dividing the black majority it uses various coersive methods. 

1. The land question, its sensitivity and the issue of reincorporation of the homelands 

2. The importance of the traditional leaders as well as the issue of the role they play and how they need to adapt to the present situation and embrace democratic practice. 

3. Building of Alliances. 

1. ANC/SACP and COSATU 

2. The Patriotic Front 

3. A Government of National Unity 

4. Violence 

1. The Peace Accord 

2. The strategy to shift repression to the homelands 

3. Bisho and the right to political freedom of speech and association 

4. 28 people being buried at Bisho today 

5. International monitoring: our initiative at the UN 

5. The Drought 

The Northern Transvaal is the worst hit by the drought in terms of human suffering. The region has received than 50% of its annual rainfall. 

1. The drought is not a political tool, the present position of the NP in terms of using drought relief funds to recruit for the NP. The role of the SADF in building a character of the NP as the benevolent godfather. 

2. We have a seven year drought cycle. 

 3. We need to look at the proper management of water resources 

4. We need to develop the correct procedures to assist rural communities to upgrade water supplies. 

5. The responsibility for this planning has to rest the government, industry and the community and the people with the least resources should not be used as tools for the government's manipulation. Disaster must be treated as a national emergency not an electioneering tool.</body></text></speech>