I Nelson Mandela, President of the African National Congress, have known Tembi Kingston all her life. I have followed her progress as she grew up. He father, a deeply principled man, was my close friend and Adelaide has been equally close to me during my years in jail. I entrusted the care of my grandson to her during holidays when he was at school. 
Tembi has asked me to provide a statement for her. 
Firstly I should say that South Africa having finally started on the road to democracy, is undergoing historic changes. I believe that our country will become a peaceful and economically productive one. The spotted violence we are experiencing at the present time will, I believe diminish. Certainly there is no danger for Tembi and the children in the Northern Suburbs. I live there myself," as do many other black families. it is quiet, pleasant and ideally suited for raising children. There are parks, bicycle rides, cricket and soccer clubs. My daughter and her four children intend moving there also. 
I have on maw occasion seen Tembi's children, the last time was at a soccer match when Arsenal came to South Africa. As usual I was warmly greeted. On this occasion Tembi was with Sacha he seemed as happy as always. 
Although Tembi is not involved in politics, she and her children have been fortunate in benefitting from the very high regard in which her parents are held. This is across the different racial groups. Indeed State President De Klerk had asked to attend the funeral of our late National Chairman. 
Some time ago I called Tembi to ask what I could do practically to help her. Specifically with regards to her finding some kind of employment. I have no fears that she will be able to find an interesting job in South Africa. She explained that despite her wish to be independent financially, she felt this would not be ;possible until the children were somewhat older. I understood this My own experiences have left me in no doubt as to the importance or a mother in the lives of her children. At this point I feel I should add a character reference. 
Tembi is an intelligent girl. I have found her to be honest, direct and unpretentious. She loves her children and her efforts on their behalf since arriving back at home attest to that. She has, however, other talents which she has already started putting to good use. To date she is involved in raising funds for a crèche and nursery school in Tamboville, she has found sponsorship, builders and architects, to erect a recreational sports facility there also. She hosts charitable functions to raise awareness and funds for underprivileged children. She has set up The Oliver Tambo Foundation on her own initiative. This, once the necessary legal requirements have been met, will be launched in South Africa and the United States of America. I have no doubt whatsoever that Tembi can make a very positive contribution in building up our country through channels such as these. 
I further believe that her children have a bright and exciting future here. I understand that they have received good reports and are enjoying school and the many friends they have made. 
At out last meeting I assured Tembi of my support. Her father has now passed away and as my dearest friend, I must step into his shoes. As I told her at the time, she must now call me "O.R.'. 
I have known Martin Kingston through Tembi. I welcomed him as the son of Oliver, who tried to help Martin, as did Adelaide in any way that might progress his career. This would mainly take the form of introductions, contacts and of course being seen with them at public functions. I have, whenever the opportunity has presented itself, made time for Martin as a member of my extended family. I was therefore somewhat surprised to learn that Martin had the impression that the ANC had appointed him as my personal adviser and chaperone on a recent trip to London. 
In concluding I would like to reiterate my optimism for the future of South. Africa. The majority of people look forward with hope and determination to secure for themselves and their children, a country where all peoples live in harmony.