<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1992-01-01">01 January 1992</date><text><term key="1113" /><body>Dear Friends, 

it is my privilege to be part of Africare's Bishop John T. Walker Memorial Dinner. This occasion places before all of us a number of critical issues, including Africa and her relationship with the rest of the world, the struggle for freedom, social justice and peace, and the role principled men and women play to bring about a better life for all. 

Tonight you honour two great men - John Walker, whose memory lives in our hearts, and that valiant South African man of peace, Archbishop Desmond Tutu. Both reached out to others, in their own countries and throughout the world, a beacon of hope for humanity. 

We are particularly grateful that we in Africa have such staunch friends - young and old, men and women, from all walks of life - who, although so many miles away, have taken our people, our struggle, our hopes and our fears and made them their 

own. 

South Africa stands at the dawn of a new era. The challenges facing us are enormous. Failure cannot even be contemplated. Success holds out great promise for the future. But we are grappling with problems that the world has not yet resolved. Many are man-made, such as racism, state-sponsored violence, prejudice, ignorance, poverty and disease. Yet others are the result of natural disasters, such as the horrendous drought that is forcing hundreds of thousands of people off the land, laying waste the countryside that is as barren as a desert. 

At this decisive moment in our history it is more important than ever to have friends abroad who are concerned about our 

welfare, about our future. Apartheid's crippling effects on the lives and minds of our people have been no less ravaging than the drought. Over six million people live in squatter camps in conditions of abject poverty. Millions more are unemployed. Many areas of South Africa have an illiteracy rate of 80% and over. And above all, the country is in the grip of a low intensity war against the people, erroneously referred to as violence. 

The challenge that faces us is to address these serious problems, and rise above the obstacles placed in the path to freedom. We have come this far together. The people of the world stood as one in opposition to apartheid and race discrimination. We need you to stand with us now, so that all of us can walk this last long and painful mile of our journey. To overcome the decades of deprivation will require enormous resources, both human and material. 

We want a world where, in the words of FD Roosevelt, "no one goes to bed ill-fed, ill-housed". We all have a responsibility to turn swords into ploughshares, to protect our environment, to create a country, a continent and a world in which our children can grow up to become free men and women in the land of their birth. 

Through organisations like Africare you can make a difference. Continue the noble legacy that Bishop Walker bequeathed us. Without your support in the United States, we in South Africa would never have been able to come so far. Let us finish the journey together, acting in unity for all humankind. 

I wish you all a wonderful evening and know that I am with you in spirit. 

Thank you.</body></text></speech>