<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1992-11-15">15 November 1992</date><text><term key="1110" /><body>1. (a) On behalf of the National Executive Committee of the African National Congress, the African National Congress membership and on my own behalf, I extend warm fraternal greetings to the delegates assembled at the 

conference. 

The Conference is one of the most important solidarity conferences ever held in the United States of America. It has brought together the finest and most widely representative fighters for democracy from South Africa 

and the United States. 

I salute you all. 

1. (b) It is your tireless and selfless activities, in support of our struggle that has forced the Apartheid Regime to open the prison gates. To unban political organisations, to allow the return of our people from exile and to seek a negotiated resolution of the South African crisis. We will always remember and appreciate the historical contribution made by the International Solidarity Movement. 

2. The theme of your conference " Support for the ANC and Other Democratic Forces " underlines the basic tasks confronting us. We have not yet achieved our objective of a non-racial, non- sexist. Democratic and united South Africa. It is therefore vitally important to continue to mobilise international pressure against Apartheid South Africa. On the other hand Conference should be looking at concrete measures to be embarked upon in order to consolidate and defend the new democracy that will surely come into being sooner than later. 

The legacy of apartheid has imposed herculean tasks for a New Democratic South Africa. We will need all the assistance that can be given to help us meet these challenges. We are confident that the people of the United States of America will not be found wanting. 

3. At this juncture I must express my profound and deepest regret for not being able to participate in your very important conference. I am sure that you will appreciate that our nation is experiencing one of the most serious crisis in our painful history. Violence continues to engulf large areas of our country to a degree never seen before. Hundreds of innocent men, women and children continue to die at the hands of assassins, who, having failed to hoodwink the people to support racial discrimination, domination and arrogance now want to terrorise the people to accept unacceptable schemes in order to perpetuate the system of Apartheid. 

The negotiations process stalled because of continuing violence. Recently and belatedly the Government of South Africa accepted the need to implement certain measures to tackle the serious problem of violence in our country. Consequently the process of negotiations has once again commenced, despite continuing attempts to sabotage the process. The future of our country and our people demands that we move as quickly as possible to the establishment of an interim government of national unity, and following this, within a period of nine months to democratic elections for a constituent assembly. These issues are complex and delicate and they have compelled myself and many of my colleagues to postpone all international programmes and remain in South Africa in order to concentrate on the challenges facing us. We apologise for any inconvenience caused. 

The African National Congress, however , recognising the importance of this New York Conference has released many of our outstanding leaders and activists to participate in the Conference. Together we must map out the programme of action that will ensure that all obstacles to democracy are removed and that a genuine democracy is established in South Africa as soon as possible. 

I wish conference all success in its deliberations, 

With your support victory is assured. 

AMANDLA</body></text></speech>