Master of Ceremonies, 

Hon Bill Clinton, President of the United States of America, 

Prof Martin Meyerson, President-Emeritus of the University of Pennsylvania and Chairman of the 1993 Intenational Selection Commission and members of the Commission, 

Mr Ronald J. Naples, President of We the People 2000, 

Hon Ed Rendell, Mayor of this historic city of Philadelphia; 

President F.W. de Klerk, and fellow-honoree; 

Distinguished guests, friends, ladies and gentlemen: 

It will have seemed strange to some, that two South Africans, with respective histories as different as those of this year's honourees, should share the honour of receiving the eminent Philadelphia Liberty Medal. 

Equally, it will have seemed strange to some we, as fighters for liberation, are, together with those who have been the captains of apartheid, involved in processes leading to the democratic transformation of South Africa. 

Some who know have also made the point that it was strange, two hundred years ago, that those who designed the world's first democratic constitution in this very city, should have permitted the system of slavery to continue. 

Strange though all these things might be, and evocative of different responses, they nevertheless speak to one issue. They speak to the durability of the glorious vision that gave birth to the independence of this country and to the United States Constitution. 

They affirm the correctness and invincibility of the truths and the ideals of liberty, equality and the pursuit of human happiness contained in that historic document as well as the Declaration of Independence. 

It is therefore with a deep sense of humility that we stand here today to receive a Medal which bestows on us as individuals, as a movement and as a people the stature of the founding fathers who crafted your Constitution. 

The great African-American, Frederick Douglass, spoke in Rochester, New York on July 5th, 1852, on the topic - "The Meaning of July Fourth for the Negro". 

Here is some of what he said: 

" Fellow citizens, I am not wanting in respect for the fathers of this republic…They were great men too - great enough to give frame to a great age…In their admiration of liberty, they lost sight of all other interests…Their statesmanship looked beyond the passing moment, and stretched away in strength into the distant future. They seized upon eternal principles, and set a glorious example in their defence." 

It would be a rare honour to those who will draw up our own Constitution that they should thus be described by the democratic commentators and freedom activists of our own age and of the future. 

It is a moving thing for us, that we, who represent forces that have still to proclaim that freedom's day has come, are today being handed the baton in the race to liberty, at whose starting point, in Philadelphia, stood the great men of whom, the freed slave, Frederick Douglass, spoke with such warmth and charity of spirit. 

But we would not be true to Frederick Douglass, if we did not recall other things that this great intellect and fighter for freedom said in the same address, a hundred and forty one years ago. 

Frederick Douglass asked the poignant question: 

" Are the great principles of political freedom and natural justice, embodied in that Declaration of Independence, extended to us? …" 

Struck by an almost palpable grief, he went on to say: 

"The rich inheritance of justice, liberty, prosperity and independence, bequeathed by your fathers, is shared by you, not by me… This Fourth July is yours, not mine. You may rejoice, I must mourn." 

" Fellow-citizens, above your national, tumultuous joy, I hear the mournful wail of millions… My subject, then, fellow-citizens, is American slavery. I shall see this day and its popular characteristics from the slave's point of view." 

This is perhaps the greatest challenge we face as we struggle for the new birth of freedom, that none within our country should in future proclaim that justice, liberty and prosperity are not shared by them, as did Frederick Douglass, the black enslaved and the women of this country. 

In the struggle for real change and a just peace, we will have to overcome the terrible heritage of the insult to human dignity, the inequalities, the conflicts and antagonisms that are the true expression of the apartheid system. 

To overcome them we will have to succeed to build one nation in which all South Africans will be to one another sister and brother, sharing a common destiny and shorn of the terrible curse of having to define themselves in racial and ethnic terms. 

We must therefore negotiate and agree a constitution and a Bill of Rights that are both truly democratic and fully guarantee the fundamental human rights of all our citizens. 

We must engage in the challenging process of the fundamental reconstruction of our country in all spheres 

of human endeavour - 

so that the liberation of both the oppressed and the oppressor from the tyranny of racism becomes tangible, the equality of all, actual, and the recognition of the dignity of every human being, real; 

so that the emancipation of our people, for which you also struggled, becomes a manifest and genuine continuation - of what you sought to achieve when you declared your independence, adopted your constitution, your Bill of Rights and your civil rights instruments; 

of what you tried to realise when you went to war for the unity of your country, the emancipation of the slaves and, later, the destruction of fascism; 

so that our emancipation becomes a manifest and genuine continuation of the struggles you have waged, 

when you have striven to attain what you thought and think was and is just, 

as you grappled with the reality of what is for untold millions, both inside and outside this country, but a dream deferred - 

the multitudes that are hungry, homeless and jobless; 

deprived of access to good health and knowledge; 

caught in the web of violence, drug abuse and hopeless despair; 

and stand at the city gates, with no other possibility to make their voices heard than to put to the torch the rich inheritance which Frederick Douglass denounced, not because it was unworthy in itself, but because it had betrayed itself by excluding others who were as human as those who were the beneficiaries of the vision of freedom and prosperity to which this city is heir. 

You, the peoples of the United States of America and of the world stood with us as we fought for our political emancipation. We urge you to stay the course until freedom is won. 

We call on you to invest in the new South Africa, to share with us your expertise and technology so that we come together in a joint venture that will produce the mutually beneficial result of democracy, prosperity, peace 

and stability for both our countries, friendship and cooperation between our peoples and enable us both to own 

the liberation of South Africa as a common prize. 

Let the Philadelphia Liberty Medal, which we are humbled to receive from the hand of the President of the United States, serve as the lodestar which guides us, as South Africans, as we march to freedom. 

Let it be our pledge to you that we shall seize on the eternal principles of justice, liberty and peace and set an example in their defence. 

Let it be the seal of an unbreakable treaty of friendship between our peoples which will be durable, 

because it responded to the clarion call which Frederick Douglass made, 

because it respected the memory of those who have perished through the ages, in the quest for liberty, 

because it pays homage to those whose sacrifices have enabled us as South Africans to say that freedom is in sight! 

We thank you for the honour you have bestowed on our people, both black and white, and will convey to them your noble sentiments of respect, love and solidarity.