<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1993-06-23">23 June 1993</date><text><term key="164" /><body>The Presidents of the ANC and IFP met together with their respective delegations for wide-ranging discussions. 

Discussions were frank, meaningful and productive and were conducted in a sprit of mutual respect and concern for the future. 

Out of these discussions there has come a determination to seek ways and means of bringing about peace and success in negotiations. 

A joint undertaking between the two leaders has been drawn up and is attached. 

In addition it was agreed that it is time for the ANC and the IFP to bury the past and to look to the future. 

We will work together to promote national reconciliation and a democratic future for our country. 

Both the ANC and the IFP, like all other political parties who are helping to make a new South Africa, have a right to exist and must cooperate in the creation of the new society. 

We recognise that each of our organisations has a legitimate right to exist and to participate peacefully in the democratic process. 

We agree that a meeting of the signatories to the National Peace Accord should be convened as soon as possible in order to ratify recommendations for the strengthening of the Peace Accord. 

We recognise that if we are to set an example of reconciliation for our people, we must make it clear that both the ANC and the IFP support free political activity and reject the concept of no-go areas. 

We have agreed to ourselves conduct joint symbolic visits to persons and places which are of great significance to our respective organisations and to share joint platforms in strife-torn areas to bring about peace. 

We have also agreed that there is a need in both our organisations to ensure that agreements reached at national and regional levels find expression among the people. Peace and democracy must become the property of all South Africans. 

We commit ourselves to taking active steps to ensure the agreements we have reached today are communicated to all of our members and supporters and are implemented at all levels of our organisations. 

We have both agreed that the elimination of apartheid and the creation of a non-racial, non-sexist, democracy through the Multi-Party Negotiating Process are vital steps which must be taken to improve relationships between us and to bring about peace in South Africa. We have agreed to establish constructive bilateral relations between our respective organisations at the negotiations process. We will seek through this mechanism to resolve the differences which remain outstanding between us, including differences over constitutional issues. 

We reiterate our agreement that there will be prohibition on the carrying of dangerous weapons, which are detrimental to the peace process, to political meetings and rallies. We also deplore the proliferation of arms which are being acquired freely and which are being used to decimate human life. We call for tighter control of all illegal arms by all persons and parties. 

Together we commit ourselves to lead for peace and democracy and to make the agreements reached here today historically significant. 

JOINT UNDERTAKING BETWEEN NELSON MANDELA, PRESIDENT OF THE ANC AND INKOSI MANGOSUTHU BUTHELEZI, PRESIDENT OF IFP AND CHIEF MINISTER OF KWAZULU 

I. BASIC PRINCIPLES 

1 South Africa has reached a crucial stage on the path to democracy. After centuries of colonial domination and apartheid, our country is poised for a major breakthrough leading to the establishment of a united, non-racial, non-sexist and democratic order and a government based on the will of the people. 

2. The achievements made thus far are a result of the efforts and sacrifices made by -the people of our country and international support for a democratic settlement. The people's aspirations will find expression in democratic elections for a government of their choice, and measures aimed at reconstructing our country to the benefit of all and bringing about national reconciliation. 

3. The ANC and the IFP recognise the historic importance of this moment. We jointly reaffirm our commitment to the speedy resolution of the problems that remain so that our society can at least find peace and occupy its rightful place among the world community of nations. 

4. Violence remains one of the most serious impediments in the endeavour to realise these objectives. The ANC and the IFP acknowledge that every life lost is a serious indictment on the system of apartheid, our own organisations as well as other political leaders; and that it behoves all peace-loving South Africans to engender within our communities the spirits of peace and tolerance. 

5. On behalf of the ANC and the IFP, we hereby reaffirm our commitment to the agreements reached in previous bilateral meetings as well as the National Peace Accord. We jointly commit ourselves to reaching an agreement together with the other signatories to strengthen the National Peace Accord, and to abide by its strengthened provisions. We hereby commit ourselves to the peaceful resolution of the problems of our country, and to a constructive approach in dealing with matters under discussion in multi-party negotiations. 

In order to help contribute to the atmosphere necessary for a peaceful transition to democracy, we commit ourselves to the following principles: 

II. ORGANISATIONAL RELATIONS 

1 The IFP and the ANC are two independent organisation founded to pursue what each organisation perceives as the interest of the country and its people. 

2. The two organisations share the common objective of ridding SA of the scourge of apartheid and its consequences. Insofar as we share these common perspectives, we are duty-bound to co-operate in their realisation. 

3. Where the ANC and IFP differ on mechanisms to this end, we commit ourselves to discuss these differences in a spirit of tolerance and mutual respect, taking into account that the interests of SA and its people transcend these differences. 

4. It is therefore the responsibility of both organisations to ensure that our supporters, members and particularly leaders at all levels, promote a healthy relationship between them based on such mutual respect and tolerance. 

III NORMAL POLITICAL ACTIVITY 

1. The common objectives that the two organisations as well as other parties share, require that there be an atmosphere of peace among all South Africans, freedom of association, assembly and other basic human rights. 

2. We therefore commit ourselves to promote the creation of such an atmosphere, and to do all in our power to prevent violations of these principles by our members and supporters. In particular, urgent measures need to be undertaken to ensure free political activity throughout SA. This entails, inter alia; 

2.1 The recognition by our members and supporters of the right of all individuals to hold their own views, and their right to express these views without intimidation and violence; while at the same time eschewing mutual vilification. 

2.2 Where either of our organisations are able to do so - we shall ensure that other organisations are allowed to canvass their views and that they are afforded the necessary facilities to do so. This should apply to both urban and rural areas. 

2.3 Both the IFP and ANC recognise the right of people to assemble and give expression to their grievances and the parties they support provided that such manifestations are in keeping with the letter and spirit of the National Peace Accord. To this end the IFP and the ANC agree that if and when either party convenes a demonstration, protest or any other form of mass action, it will ensure that: 

2.3.1 it has given priority to the need to promote peace; 

2.3.2 the action will avoid deliberate provocation of opponents, injury to persons or damage to property; 

2.3.3 the structures of the Peace Accord will be kept fully and timeously informed and will be utilised to maximum effect; 

2.3.4 good faith negotiations will occur with all relevant parties and the security forces regarding the proposed action; 

2.3.5 all agreements reached regarding the proposed action will be binding, and the convening party will comply with them and do everything reasonably possible to ensure its members are aware of the agreements; 

2.3.6 sufficient marshals will be provided to ensure that the proposed action is peaceful and disciplined; 

2.3.7 all reasonable steps will be taken to make sure that no weapons are carried with unlawful intent; 

2.3.8 in making its decision as to whether the action would be embarked upon, the convening party will give due cognisance to the political climate prevailing at the time and the appropriateness of the proposed action; 

2.3.9 the convening party will plan the route of any demonstration so as to provide for a specific place where it is to start, the route which is to be followed and a place where the march should end and where and how marchers should disperse; 

2.3.10 provision will be made for effective means of communication between the conveners of the action, marshals, peace committee monitors, the police and any other relevant party during the action and immediately thereafter. 

3. Realising that the problem of violence and legitimate law enforcement should also be addressed in the context of the unfolding transition, we commit ourselves to contribute constructively to the multilateral negotiations on multiparty control of all armed formations. In particular, we agree that all proposals regarding armed formations in the country should be considered in the light of a single, over-riding objective; to establish impartial, accountable, effective and legitimate security forces for a democratic South Africa. To this end, we specifically endorse the proposals made in the Fourth Report of the Technical Committee on Violence at the Multi-Party Negotiating Process regarding the adoption of a series of phased, confidence building measures within a common framework to achieve this objective. We recognise that within this common framework a clear distinction will have to be drawn between statutory and non-statutory armies on the one hand and police forces on the other during the transition to democracy and thereafter. This distinction is consistent with our view that policing functions should be clearly distinguished from military functions and our view that the various armies should play no role in the elections process which lies before us, while the various police forces and a multi-party peace-keeping force will be required to fulfil ongoing law and order functions. 

4. Where there are disputes between us, including disputes regarding either party's freedom to canvass its views and be afforded the necessary facilities to do so or regarding the exercise of the right to freedom of assembly, we agree to attempt to resolve these disputes in a constructive manner. We agree that the primary mechanisms for dispute resolution between us are those contained in the National Peace Accord and direct meetings and liaison between our two organisations. 

5. Realising that apartheid and the variety of struggles against it have had particularly serious consequences for South Africa's youth, and that there is a need to constructively channel the energies and hope of the youth, we commit ourselves to participate together in the development of a peace-corps/youth services under the auspices of the National Peace Accord. 

IV JOINT MECHANISMS 

1 In order to promote healthy and constructive interaction between our organisations, we commit ourselves to strengthen and expedite the work of the joint liaison structures between our two organisations. We call on these structures to speed up their work aimed at finalising detailed agreements on matters of mutual concern for ratification by the respective executives. 

2. In order to obviate some of the problems that beset relations between the two organisations after previous bilateral meetings, we agree that such joint mechanisms should include measures aimed at monitoring progress in the implementation programmes agreed upon and dealing with such violations as may occur. Further, we pledge to ensure that problems that arise in this relationship will be handled first and foremost through the channels agreed upon rather through the media; and that such contact will not be broken off simply as a result of differences that might emerge. 

3. In the endeavour to ensure that the relations between our organisations find expression among the people, we undertake to initiate and encourage activities among our structures at all levels. This will include: 

3.1 Joint mass rallies, meetings and marches by local as well as regional structures - which should be undertaken as a matter of urgency to relate to one another in this spirit of co-operation, mutual respect and tolerance. 

4. None among us should see it necessary, no matter how serious the point of disagreement, to resort to violence. Those who seek to exploit whatever differences may exist between the two organisations for their own ends, will then stick out like a sore thumb. 

5. Great possibilities exist for the final resolution of the political problems that have gripped our country for decades and even centuries. We owe it to ourselves, our children and generations to come, not to squander this historic opportunity. 

6. The future of peace and democracy for which many have sacrificed their lives is within reach. Let us grasp it with both hands.</body></text></speech>