<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1993-05-12">12 May 1993</date><text><term key="1167" /><body>Mr Chairman 

Mr Gleitsman 

Comrade Walter Sisulu, Deputy President of the ANC 

Members of the National Executive Committee of the ANC. 

Distinguished Guests, Ladies and Gentlemen 

Comrades and Friends 

I am very delighted to be here with you tonight and feel greatly honoured to receive the International Activists Award from the Gleitsman Foundation. The honour bestowed on me by your esteemed Foundation testifies to the recognition of the efforts of the African National Congress and all the democratic forces in our country, struggling to dismantle a system that has been declared a crime against humanity. 

We of the African National Congress feel greatly honoured to have been considered to be amongst the first of those recognized by your Foundation internationally, for their contribution in the course of social justice, peace and democracy. 

It is the situation that obtain in our country that has propelled many sons and daughters of this land, men and women, including children, who at a very early age take up serious responsibilities in service of our people. The struggle for democracy and social justice has produced many heroes and heroines, and it is on their behalf that we stand here today to accept your honour of their sacrifices. The late Helen Joseph, a stalwart of our movement, who tonight received a posthumous award is one amongst many of those heroines. 

Mr Chairman 

The challenge facing all those who seek democracy in our country today, is that we should ensure that the achievements registered by our struggle are further consolidated and protected. We have to resist all attempts by those who want to divert us from our common goal of a democratic, unitary, non-racial state achieved through peaceful negotiations by all political actors in this country. 

We view with great concern the deliberate provocation by rightwing elements aimed at sparking off a racial civil war. We wonder when will the power that be stop their soft handling of the rightwing, who continue to pose a threat to the democratic process in this country. The brutal killing of our leaders and activists, attacks by rightwing forces against ANC members and our property as was the case last weekend in Pampierstad when two organizers of the ANC were way-laid and brutally attacked. The recent exposure of another plot to assassinate Comrade Joe Slovo, all these are deliberate actions taken to force us back into a violent confrontation. 

We want to put it on record that is remains the responsibility of this government to ensure the safety of all citizens including our members and leaders. We however wish to warn that the patience of our people cannot remain endless as they continue to be subjected to brutalisation and murder. 

Mr Chairman 

We are convinced that there is urgent need to agree on an election date and the establishment of the multiparty transitional Executive Council, a Subcouncil on Security and Defence, an independent Electoral Commission and an independent media commission. The establishment of the transitional Executive Council is important as this will provide the mechanism for all political parties to jointly address matters such as control of all armed forces and police, which would make a decisive contribution in helping us to contain and reduce the level of violence. 

The ANC remains committed to ensuring that our movement forward to a democratic South Africa continue to gain momentum and remains unstoppable. 

Most importantly, we will continue to play a full and dynamic role with the support of the international anti apartheid movement and democratic governments throughout the world to remove the scourge of apartheid, and to ensure that South Africa becomes a member of a democratic world order where all are cherished equally. 

It gives me great pleasure to accept this prestigious and important award. 

Thank you.</body></text></speech>