We feel greatly honoured to be given the opportunity to send a message to this important gathering of the Greek Business Community in our country. 

Your gathering takes place during a important period, when our country is preparing itself for historic changes. It is changes that are going to leave a permanent mark on all our communities. It is changes that demand from all of us the courage to participate fully in shaping the future of this country. 

We take this opportunity to call upon the Greek Community in South Africa, to take their rightful position in the democratisation process currently unfolding in our land. 

We have been fully aware of the significant role the Greek community is playing in industry and commerce. We believe greater opportunities are going to arise as a result of democratisation, and therefore it is going to be very important for you to prepare yourselves to make your contribution through investment and further expansion of your existing enterprises. Positive developments in this area are going to be very crucial in order to complement the political democracy that will be achieved through the April 27th elections. 

The present period presents all of us with considerable challenges. By the end of November we expect the Transitional Executive Council to be established This will signal a crucial phase in the process toward democratisation. The TEC shall help to create a climate conducive for free and fair elections, as well as seek to lower the levels of violence. 

As for the African National Congress, we remain committed to pursuing the road that will bring about security, freedom and democracy for all the people of South Africa, including South African minorities. That is why we have continued to demand a Bill of Rights that entrenches the freedom of worship, language, association, movement, language, employment and culture for all. It is for these rights and many others that the ANC engaged in struggle for so many years. 

We look forward to be with you side by side with us as we enter this new and challenging period. 

Build democracy with us. INVEST IN THE FUTURE. Thank You 
