00. Salutations. 
01. Within close on two decades, the Transport and General Workers' Union has evolved into a force to be reckoned with on the labour front. Its history is full of inspiring instances of genuine commitment to the rights of the working person as well as the broader issues of the liberation effort. Notable amongst these are the stirring battles waged by the TGWU in support of 
 international sanctions through the mobilization of long haul truckers and dockworkes handling citrus products; the memorable PUTCO strike as well as the sometimes underrated elevation of gender issues to a position of priority in the labour front, among other examples. As a broadly based organisation, the TGWU enjoys the advantage of having been able to organise in several industrial sectors - a fact which makes it an extremely important factor in both the political terrain and the dynamics of labour bargaining. 
02. Having said that, we must state that now, more than ever before, the TGWU must position itself firmly among defenders of democratic goals. In the current situation, trade unions are in a unique position to help reinforce and accelerate the process of transition in a manner that can benefit the lot of the working masses. This objective can be attained through the intensification of educational projects aimed at improving the capacity of labour to press for a fair dispensation both at the negotiating table and at the level of industrial bargaining . The time for unions to take their rightful position in the process of political transformation is now. 
03. We of the ANC have always believed in the right of working class organisations to independence. This is an ideal that we have cherished and fought for throughout our existence. It is also a matter which adds rather than subtracts from the substance of positive political change. [In this regard, the ANC has no intention of revoking its convictions in preference to a path that could pit labour against the general national interest to be represented/articulated by a new democratic government. In other words] The ANC government shall and must be seen to act after a fashion that galvanises civil society as well as its organs. To this end, we are promoting the idea of a Reconstruction Accord between Labour Federations and the progressive section of the political establishment. In our view, such an accord should form the bedrock upon which should be founded the dialectics of interaction between civil society and the future state. Any ill-advised alternative to this approach will throw up repercussions whose consequences could be so dire as to border on civil dislocation. 
04. There is much concern presently over certain views regarding the alliance between labour and the liberation movement. 
This alliance was and remains a natural outcome of the historical processes which have shaped our struggle- the liberation of the oppressed and the ushering in of a free, democratic, non-sexist and non-racial order. The motive force of that struggle has always been the oppressed black masses irrespective of their different stations in life. This means that the various sections of our people had to join the broad struggle against racial oppression. 
05. Precisely because of this reason the shape and content of the alliance must assume a different manner which corresponds to the pace of change. As a matter of fact, time will soon be upon us when, after the installation of a government of national unity, we should be able to say that emphasis should be placed only on fair cooperation. A new government cannot entertain "mountain-topism" at the expense of the legitimate rights of the people to parley and make demands. In truth, this kind of relationship is a healthy one since it opens government to scrutiny, public criticism and releases the energies of labour to pressure government to deliver our promises made and beat the path of all-round development. The modalities of arriving at such a situation must emerge from on-going discussions and negotiations between all concerned, without favouring any particular group or group of interests. 
06. We see no reason why, with enough discernible sense of goodwill across the board, such a project should fail. However, the measure of our success should be determined by appropriate guarantees on workers' rights being built into the new constitution. Coupled with this, will be the need to put in place affirmative action programmes for the empowerment of the underprivileged. As for us in the ANC, we have no doubt about the depth of our intention to meet as far as humanly possible, the fundamental aspirations of the people as a whole. Rights of workers to strike against a democratic government of the latter fails to deliver the goods. 
7. We have now arrived at a historic milepost in the progress towards a new South Africa. Nevertheless, the situation remains fluid and therefore fraught with concealed dangers. The fact that we are engaged in the preparations for an election should not dupe us into complacency. Even as we speak of a focused thrust at the World Trade Centre, we must continue to address those issues which tend to draw us apart in a manner that will stress those which hold us together. 
08. We are concerned, like everyone else, about those marauding forces which ceaselessly and meticulously seek to drive wedges between us. WE are equally bothered by those who move from cities and towns, villages and homesteads, schools and universities, churches, mosques, and every other place of worship, sowing seeds of death and destruction with the express purpose of derailing the democratisation process in our country. Our only choice is to hit back at them with a political competence of a higher moral quality, intelligent courage and united action. 
09. The jealousies and divisions which seem to afflict many of our organisations must be consigned to the grave. The TGWU and the rest of the labour movement has a responsibility to strive for sustained unity in the various sectors in order to secure a vantage position from which it can influence the direction of the post-election reconstruction programme. 
[10. Elections and Electioneering. Quo Vadis?] 