<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1994-06-12">12 June 1994</date><text><term key="1377" /><body>Honourable Chairperson 
Distinguished delegates 
Brothers and Sisters 
It is a moment of joy for me to once more join you at the Annual Convention of the National Association for the Advancement of Coloured People. The memories of our meeting last year are deeply etched in my heart, one of the few occasions that shall always stir deep emotions in me. 
Unfortunately, we could not be with you in person at this annual union. Time constraints and the new pressures of political office have made it impossible. Such are the vagarities of life, that the more we progress, the more are the challenges that we have to surmount. This is the position today as we celebrate the common achievement of humanity, an achievement of black people of the world: the advent of a free, non-racial, non-sexist and democratic South Africa. 
If we are ecstatic at this historic moment, this is because it has been hard and long in coming. 
If we tend to value it above everything else, this is because it has been achieved at such tremendous sacrifice. If we cherish it with such passion, this is because we saw the determination among millions of 
ordinary South Africans who, as W E B du Bois advised many decades ago, valued "the privilege and duty of voting". 
And so, dear brothers and sisters, we have together expanded the frontiers of democracy and human civilisation. The renaissance of the black people of the world has come to pass - to be free, proud and equal citizens of the world. 
Therefore, to us, this year's Annual Convention of the Association is a historic one. Together we ushered in the 20th Century with the formation of our organisations: the National Association and the African National Congress. As we trudge to the horizon of the new century, your brothers and sisters in South Africa are able to join you in the chorus: Free at last! Thank God Almighty, we are free at last! 
We utter these venerable words, in tribute to the stalwarts who should have been with us today but are no more. The course that W E B du Bois, Marcus Garvey, Martin Luther King and many more charted, shall forever guide us in our efforts. 
We who have had the honour, in our life-time, to reap the fruits of their efforts, face a mammoth challenge. For, what we celebrate today is but the first harvest in a continuing cycle of seasons of hard work: to plant, to tend and reap the fruits of our labour. 
It has befallen us to be victim of that famous Chinese curse: may you live in interesting times - for us, the new and historic times to shed the security of agitation and resistance, and don the cap of reconstruction and development. 
South Africans have gone a long way in ensuring reconciliation and national consensus around the main issues that face the nation. But, two months into political office, it is more apparent than ever before that our freedom will be meaningless if we do not rapidly implement socio-economic programmes to improve the lot of the ordinary people. 
We are at one, that the true measure of success for our fledgling democracy, and lasting security for society as a whole, lie in creating a better life for all South Africans. This we have set out to do with determination. And with your assistance, we are confident that we shall succeed. 
We are therefore encouraged by the new partnership that we are developing with our neighbours as well as the industrialised and developing countries of the world. In particular, news of your proposal for a Mission in South Africa, has been warmly received. Yours is truly a unique initiative. For, it underlines the centrality of people-to-people relations in building a new world. Above all, we are profoundly moved by your preparedness to join us in our endeavours despite the challenges that your communities face at home. 
South Africans look forward to many years of co-operation between us. No doubt, this will benefit communities in both countries as well as the rest of Africa. So that in the near future, when our lips dare utter the words: Free at Last! - we shall be referring to more than just freedom from political bondage. We shall also be declaring all our citizens' freedom from ignorance and poverty. 
I once more thank you for the invitation to exchange views with you, and wish this year's Convention a success. I hope that soon we will meet in a physical reunion of celebration and rededication to meet the new challenges. 
Thank You. </body></text></speech>