Until now a lot of preparatory work has been done as far as the formulation of legislation, the inauguration of political heads, meetings of the first Cabinet of National Unity and Parliament and other necessary preliminary steps are concerned. Progress has also been made with the process of rationalization. I am aware that this is a major task. I am also aware that good progress is being made with the financial arrangements of the provinces. Today is, however, the first joint action by political leaders to actually start implementing the system of provincial government. 
It is a privilege for me and my two deputy executive presidents to welcome you all to this very important occasion. I realize that, after having just recently been elected and appointed to the very demanding position that you now hold, it must have been very difficult for you to leave your office for this meeting. At the same time, I am convinced that you too are of the opinion that the need for this meeting is of the utmost importance. I therefore thank you for fitting this meeting into your busy agenda. 
We are all aware of the fact that we have developed a provincial system which is unique to the South African circumstances. There is no similar model elsewhere in the world which we could use as an exact proto-type. It will therefore require innovative thinking by every office-bearer and administrator to achieve the results envisaged in the Constitution. 
The concept of co-operation, consultation and the attainment of consensus forms the basis of, and runs like a golden thread through our entire Constitution. Without derogating from the autonomy of provinces, it will be necessary for all of us to act in this spirit, of co-operation in order to achieve our goals. We have created expectations, not only to the many millions of voters who are dependent upon the success of our attempts in this regard, but also to the outside world. We can only succeed if we are all prepared to act in partnership with each other, although we are independent of each other. 
Without pre-empting your discussion and decisions today, I can well imagine that regular meetings of a similar nature will be necessary to advance the process of implementation and development of provincial affairs. I am also sure that the various line function ministries and departments will individually have to consider similar processes enabling maximum effectiveness at administrative level. At the same time the responsible departments will have to take the necessary initiative to ensure that the process of negotiation proceeds at all levels of government, the least of which is at local government level. It must furthermore be remembered that the negotiating process did not cease when the Constitution was adopted in Parliament. The negotiating process must still form the basis upon which the final constitutional dispensation, which will obviously affect the concept of provincial government, is to be finalized. 
I have looked at your agenda. Clearly there are important issues to be addressed today. It is my sincere wish, and also that of my colleagues, that you proceed in the very spirit that I have emphasized. I am positive that if you can succeed today, it will lay a sound foundation on which to build in the future. We wish you well in your deliberations.