<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1994-09-14">14 September 1994</date><text><term key="1554" /><body>The PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC: Mr President, before I deal with the issues which have been raised here, I would like to state that I experienced the performance of Senator Moorcroft and the others, like Senator Swanepoel and Senator Jooste, with mixed feelings. It was encouraging to see some of our White colleagues speaking an indigenous language so well. In fact, I am tempted to feel that here we have the pillars on which we should start building the new South Africa. [Applause.] However, I also looked at their performance with trepidation. Judging from the ovation they attracted, I wondered what would happen to some of us if Senator Moorcroft contested the Presidency of the Republic of South Africa. [Laughter.] But, that is all part of democracy. 
When I listened to the comments made here, and I say this from the bottom of my heart, I believed that the provinces in this country made the right choices when electing the senators. The senators are worthy of the trust placed in them by the people in the nine provinces of this country. I found the comments to be constructive, as they addressed serious issues in a responsible manner. But, of course, it is clear what our mutual problem is. We are faced with a problem which some of us have raised from time to time. 
I refer to the difficulty of the White minority in this country, with its background of privileges which excluded the Blacks, not only from the centres of power, but also from enjoying the resources of this country. 
The fact is that today the White minority, which has been in power for almost three centuries, now faces the possibility of a partnership with a majority which has been excluded, and that has led to the feelings of insecurity that the democratic changes which we are hailing, might eventually lead to the domination of the Whites by the Black majority. That attitude is lacking in the approach to problems by our White counterparts in the country. -. 
That is not the only problem, however. We are also faced with the problems of Blacks who have been in the liberation movement, who have become committed to resistance and who want to continue that tradition at a time when they are required to build, and who feel they should oppose anything which will result in eventual reconciliation and nation-building. [Interjections.] 
These are the twin problems which we are facing, and it is here that king-makers are required to address these problems objectively and sincerely with a common love for and loyalty to our people and our country. 
One of the weaknesses some of our colleagues suffered from today is to use platforms of this nature for the purpose of defending their organisations, of projecting an image of their organisations as being innocent angels, and in so doing implying that it is other organisations that are the villains. That attitude can never bring about the peace that we want to build in this country. 
This does not cause any alarm to me, however. If one considers that the Government of National Unity has been in power for only four months, what has happened in this country is indeed a miracle. It is a miracle that we are sitting together today exchanging views with a view to finding a common consensus on the major national questions which had split us from top to bottom. I do not think that it could be expected that the Government of National Unity could deliver on its promises within 100 days. 
People who think this way are equating us with the United States of America, a country with an existing infrastructure and in which the new government did not have to build a new infrastructure at all. It could use the conveniences and facilities which were already there. In our case the position is totally different. We say we are going to introduce a new health scheme of free medical services for children under six and pregnant women. Where is the infrastructure for that? We do not even have enough hospitals, clinics, nurses or doctors. We have to address these issues first before that scheme can really take off. 
The same is true in the case of school-feeding schemes. Where is the infrastructure? We do not have committees to ensure that that scheme takes off, because to ensure that it takes off we must have committees of parents, students and teachers. We have to set up those structures afresh. These are some of the problems facing us in so far as we are expected to deliver on our promises. 
I am encouraged and happy about the progress that we have made. I must assure hon senators that without papering over our differences in the Government of National Unity, we are working harmoniously together. Every leader of the various parties that form the Government of National Unity is doing his best to ensure that we address our problems in a constructive manner and we have made remarkable progress. 
A young comrade has complained about the omission of 21 March as a public holiday. This was a serious omission because this day is celebrated in this country and abroad. However, the hon senator will be happy to know that the Cabinet today decided to include 21 March as one of our public holidays. [Applause.] There was naturally a lot of debate on this issue. 
However, the co-operation of all members of the Government of National Unity, enabled us to reach this decision'. We are doing so because we are trying to put our ears to the ground and to respond positively to the complaints of and demands by our people. 
Senator Ngcuka has referred to a complaint which has been made by a number of people. I am not sure whether I have told the story to some senators, but about two months ago I had a conversation with a leading Afrikaans speaking personality. He personalised the achievements of the South African people. He said I had no idea what I had done for their people, the Afrikaners. He felt that this was his country too. According to him it was not only I who was liberated, but that he was liberated too. He was prepared to serve South Africa and this was due to my strength. 
I was beginning to swell with pride when he turned around and said this was also a sign of a grave weakness on my part. He said that I was concerned with assuring Whites and neglecting my own people who put me in power. I was quick to tell him about the President's Projects which I had dealt with in Parliament. 'He knew all about those projects and he stated that the perception that had been created and which was more dangerous than facts was the one he had put to me. 
He went further and informed me that the press and mass media were not interested in the things which I was telling him. He knew that I had not abandoned my people but the perception fostered by the mass media, was that I was not attending to the affairs of the country. What strikes them is that a man who has spent a long time in jail should now adopt this conciliatory approach. They have created this perception that this is all that I am concerned with. It would appear that even my own comrades who know my activities amongst our own people, have been caught up in this propaganda fostered by the mass media. 
My comrade has now warned me that there is an element of truth in the saying that I have neglected our people and that I am now concentrating on Whites. However, I appreciate the spirit in which this has been said, because people are angry, impatient and they have suffered for centuries and they are still suffering today. I want to assure the hon senators that the RDP is there to address the basic needs of the masses of the people in this country. These needs are those of Blacks-that is Africans, Coloureds and Indians. This is the purpose of the RDP. 
The Government of National Unity in this country will stand or fall on the basis of delivery in regard to all the schemes that are involved in the RDP. Our Ministers are working 24 hours a day to ensure that we better the lives of our people, that there are sufficient jobs; sufficient schools, educational facilities and houses; electricity; transport and the introduction of clean, healthy running water. All these are intended to serve the interests and the basic needs of the masses of the people in this country. 
However, I would ask the hon senators to have the necessary patience, because one of the things that we kept .on repeating over and over again during the election campaign was that addressing the basic needs of a community was not something that could be done overnight. It is a process that will take a year, two years and even as much as five years to achieve. Unless the bon senators understand this, they will not have the necessary vision and the ability to assess the progress that has been made. The Government of National Unity, together with the co-operation of all its components, is addressing all these problems. 
I have explained in the National Assembly that I take out these white handkerchiefs and wipe my eyes, because this is a unique way of attracting attention to myself. [Laughter.] 
The question of the state of insecurity in this country has been raised. This is partly due to a lack of information. It is true that those who have not been in contact with those who are now influencing the structures of Government in this country are feeling quite insecure. However, to those who are in Government departments where they come into contact with those whom they previously regarded as their enemies, that sense of insecurity is disappearing. 
Let me give one example. On the first day I went to my office in the Union Buildings, it was completely deserted. There was not a single person, except for myself and the security guards. When I went to see Mr De Klerk in the days prior to 27 April, there was a nice smell of coffee when I entered a particular passage. On that particular day, there was no such smell, because there was nobody in that kitchen. The following day, I called in the members of staff. I shook hands with all of them, and said, “We have had our fights before, but now we are trying to bury the past and our differences." The Public Service has to be reorganised. It must reflect the composition of our people, and therefore we have to bring other sections of the community into the Public Service. However, there is no need to fear, because nobody is going to lose his job or his pension. Above all, they have had an advantage which we did not have, because they had the opportunity of education and to acquire knowledge and skills. Those who are committed to the transition will lead this process, because of the merit or the quality of the service which they can give. 
If one walks into the Union Buildings today, one would never imagine that the people who are serving us were those who came from the old Public Service. It is largely due to the manner in which the head of a department treats his colleagues in that department. I cannot pass anybody in the passage without greeting him or without shaking hands. It may well be that this is a new experience in those departments, but perceptions have completely changed, and I want to give the assurance that the greater part of this insecurity is due to the fact that there is this lack of communication and contact. 
I want to agree with and endorse the remarks about affirmative action which have been made here by Senator Prof Mchunu. Affirmative action is not intended to replace any particular individual. We are saying that opportunities which previously were closed to Africans, Coloureds, Indians, the disabled and women shall now be opened, and in our country this can be done without threatening the position of any single individual. 
The question of crime has been raised. It is a matter of concern, but do members know the origin of this unacceptably high level of crime in our country? There was a time when we organised civic guards in the townships in order to help the law enforcement agencies; it was the NP government that abolished those civic guards. 
Did senators know that we have more than 100 000 policemen in this country? Only 20% are deployed in the Black areas, and 80% are deployed in the White areas. Did senators know that hardly any Black policemen in the townships have a vehicle with which to do their duty, as the White policemen have in the White areas? Did hon senators know that in the townships one Black detective handles as many as 80 cases without a Government vehicle, by using public transport? What does one expect when there are conditions of that nature? Crime must soar, because one can fight crime only by deploying sufficient policemen in the townships, by giving them facilities to enable them to monitor crime and by ensuring that there is sufficient manpower to share these duties. 
Nevertheless, we are now addressing this question with the co-operation of all members of the Government of National Unity and we are approaching these problems not from the point of view of playing, but from the point of view of recognising that whatever happened in the past, we are now as fellow South Africans faced with the task of ensuring that an atmosphere of peace and an environment conducive to the success of the RDP are established. We cannot establish such an atmosphere by criticising and attacking one another because of past policies. We can only do so by saying that we must work together. Every talent must now be used in order to address this problem. 
Having listened to all of you here, it became quite clear that South Africa is rich not only in terms of minerals, in terms of gold and diamonds, but also in the calibre of men and women it has produced. That becomes clear in all our discussions in the National Assembly and in this Senate. One of the positive sides is that we are going to succeed in building a new South Africa. 
That brings me to the question of the truth commission. There has been a great deal of concern about this, but we do not have to fear, because the truth commission is not a court of law. That commission has no right to charge or condemn anybody. It merely places the facts on the table. It is for the police and the attorneys general to decide what to do with information which will be produced by the commission and placed before the public. The aim of the commission itself, however, is only to find out what actually happened. 
You must remember that amnesty and indemnity deal with the perpetrators of the crimes against innocent people. The truth commission is intended to address the question of the victims of those crimes. As one of our comrades on that side of the House has said, in building the spirit of reconciliation and the new nation we want to know what was committed and what it is that we are forgiving. 
You must also remember that as far as the opponents of apartheid are concerned, they were arrested and charged, evidence was led and they were convicted where there was sufficient evidence. Everybody knew what we had done. It is the same process that is going to apply, because we want to know what the defenders of apartheid have done, and we will then leave it to the courts to decide what to do. As far as we are concerned we do not want retribution, but we do want to know what it is that we are forgiving. 
That brings me to the question of the youth commission. I have discussed this question with a wide variety of organisations and I can assure you that there is no unanimity among the youth themselves on this question. [Laughter.] There are many of them who say that they do not want a Minister for youth affairs and that they do not even want this commission, but I will not go into detail now. This is a matter that is being addressed. 
Mnumzana Bhengu, halala Dlabazana, Nacolosi. [Mr Bhengu, congratulations, Dlabazana, Nacolosi.] 
The remarks that were made on the Constitution we have noted. The relevant Minister—fortunately Minister Roelf Meyer is here—is dealing with the questions in connection with the regions. He, together with his Deputy, Valli Moosa, keep me briefed about that. One will never find anybody or two persons in the Government of National Unity who are as diligent and conscientious as Minister Roelf Meyer and his Deputy, Valli Moosa. The Minister wants to make a success of his department. The questions that have been raised are the questions that he is speedily addressing, and I sincerely hope that in the near future they will be able to produce a blueprint which will satisfy all those who have raised concerns about the delays in responding to the points they have raised. 
The question of the elderly has been specifically addressed in both our manifesto and at present by the Government of National Unity. However, one should understand how these questions are addressed. It is no use just to talk. Resources have to be organised in order to ensure parity as far as pensions are concerned. Facilities have to be there for the elderly people. From the point of view of the Africans, Indians and Coloureds old age homes are not found to the same extent as amongst Whites. However, these are matters which the Department of Social Welfare, under Minister Abe Williams, is dealing with. He is working twenty four hours a day to ensure that he delivers in this regard. Finally, the question of the economy has been raised by many of the speakers here. I was tempted at times to say they were preaching to the converted. When we came out of prison, the first thing we did was to organise a meeting of no less than 400 top businessmen in this country, and we discussed with them how we should deal with the economic issues. None of the hon senators have travelled as widely as I have done. 
I have visited almost every continent in this world and my main message, right from 1990, after having called meetings of businessmen, was to urge them to come to our country and to do their feasibility studies, because at some time in the future we were going to call for the lifting of sanctions. After we had done so, they needed to have their plans ready to bring in their investments. I have gone all over the world with this message. I have seen heads of state and world bodies which have resources, in order to urge them to invest in our country. 
Tomorrow we will be having a meeting with top businessmen to continue this dialogue, but this time we will not be doing this as the ANC but as the Government of National Unity. I have invited Deputy President De Klerk and Chief Mangosuthu Buthelezi to this meeting, because we want the Government of National Unity to deal with these questions which are crucial in ensuring the creation of jobs for the five million people who are unemployed. We understand the interaction between politics and the economy, and we are on course as far as that is concerned. 
As far as Cosatu is concerned, I want to say we are dealing with an experienced and committed leadership who have fought for the betterment of conditions for the workers in this country. 
One of the problems that we have is that we have White workers who receive sometimes five times more in wages than Black workers in this country. We have a problem when we say to them they must not demand such high wages, because it will be difficult for business to create jobs for the five million people who are jobless. 
One of our difficulties is the fact that Black workers see their White counterparts enjoying privileges which are denied them, earning incomes which are not available to them, driving cars and living in the cities when our workers have to travel long distances to the townships which are far away from places of employment. 
We are faced with those problems and we must be patient, because we ourselves want to carry our people on our shoulders. 
We do not want to force ideas, however correct they may be, when there are these contradictions. It is easy to raise salaries. It is not easy to decrease the salaries of those who already enjoy them. So we are faced with that contradiction, but we are having ongoing discussions with the leaders of Cosatu and they are people who are experienced and committed to the new South Africa. Hon senators can have confidence in them that, whatever difficulties there are today, they are addressing these problems like any of us. 
However, the important thing is that the discussions here have been constructive and positive. One thing that has emerged is the idea that South Africans of all political parties should contribute positively to the promotion of the Reconstruction and Development Programme, to reconciliation and nation-building. That is why I am convinced that we have the capacity to succeed-and we shall succeed. [Applause.]</body></text></speech>