<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1994-06-29">29 June 1994</date><text><term key="1369" /><body>Mr President, ladies and gentlemmen 
A warm word of welcome to you all and thank you for taking the time to celebrate the birth of a new South Africa with us. 
It has been said that there is no better way of promoting friendship, than through sharing a good meal together. No meal is complete though without some fine wine, of which South Africa has plenty to offer, as you will rediscover on this occasion. 
In the midst of our celebrations, let us not forget the millions of hungry children all over the world who are not as fortunate to enjoy their daily bread, which is a basic human right. In this regard, I would like to congratulate the South African Chefs Association for their initiative in 1993 to gather great chefs from all over the world in South Africa, to raise money for two very deserving charities in my country. A book was also launched called "World chefs in action", and the proceeds of the sales are benefitting the hungry children of South Africa. This humanitarian gesture proved once again that we can all make a difference. 
To the competitors in the International Junior Competition, including a South Africa team, I would like to extend a special word of encouragement. By representing your respective countries in this competition, you have already proven your superior capabilities. There is, however, no institute for experience and whether your placing is first or not, you would have all gained valuable experience which nobody can take away from you. 
I am happy to note that the first ever African Regional Congress of the World Association of Cooks Societies will be held in Johannesburg during August this year, to be attended by representatives of 16 African countries. It is important that the African continent also take its rightful place on this prestigious international platform. 
I would like to take this opportunity to congratulate the South African Chefs Association on the celebration of their 20th birthday. Their list of achievements over such a short space of time is an impressive one. 
I would like to say to all the delegates attending this Congress: May you be enriched by this event and may you return to your countries with fond memories of new friendships.</body></text></speech>