<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1994-08-10">10 August 1994</date><text><term key="1251" /><body>I feel greatly honoured to be this year's recipient of the Tun Razak Award. I was emboldened to accept this prestigious award in the full knowledge that the honour you bestow on me is a recognition of the contribution that the people of South Africa as a whole, and the African National Congress in particular, have made to the ideals of humanity for freedom, peace and justice. 
We have over the years been inspired by the vision of Tun Razak of uplifting the poor by using among other measures, affirmative action in favour of the majority. The successes of the Malaysian people in building a growing and viable economy are, in part, a result of these policies. 
The people of Malaysia and South Africa have a long and special relationship. 
From those dark days, 350 years ago, when your citizens were brought to South Africa as slaves, to our common struggle against apartheid , we have been together in the fight for a better world. Today, we are in the process of building a partnership for development, as South Africa emerges into the world community of free nations. 
We remember with pride and gratitude, the role that Malaysia played in the destruction of the system of apartheid in South Africa. You were at the forefront of efforts of the Commonwealth and Non-Aligned Movement to ensure that apartheid South Africa is isolated by the international community. At the United Nations, Malaysia was active in various committees which supported our struggle and a founding member of the United Nations Special Committee Against Apartheid. 
Consistent with its anti-apartheid policies, Malaysia played a very significant role in supporting the premier liberation movement in South Africa, the African National Congress. Your support for our voter education campaign during the recent historic elections, as well as the housing project in various parts of South Africa are among the recent solidarity actions that we shall always cherish. 
The Government of National Unity in South Africa looks forward to the building of mutually-beneficial relations among our two countries in the promotion of trade, investments and technical co-operation, as well as in bilateral and multilateral endeavours to promote world peace and development. 
I once more thank you from the bottom of my heart for conferring the Tun Razak Award on me and the people of South Africa. May peace, freedom and prosperity flourish among our peoples.</body></text></speech>