<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1995-02-09">09 February 1995</date><text><term key="1375" /><body>1 Inleiding 
1.1 Ek wil die Minister bedank vir sy vernodiging aan my om sy departement te besoek, en alma! van u wat vandag hier is. Dit is die eerste geleentheid, sedert die verkiesing, dat ek 'n staatsdepartement op die manier besoek. 
1.2 Ten spyte van my besige program, het ek dit belangrik geag om die uitnodiging te aanvaar. Dit was inderdaad net my werksdruk wat veroorsaak het dat ek so lank geneem het - maande selfs - om `n geleentheid te vind om u to kom ontmoet. Ek onderneem om ook positief op uitnodiging van ander departement to reageer. 
1.3 In die geskiedkundige omwenteling waardeur ons land nou gaan, het elke sektor van ons gemeenskap sy eie rol om te vervul. Die staatsdiens, en in besonder mense soos u, in departemente dwaarsoor die land, het 'n unieke bydrae om to lewer. 
2 Transition to democracy &amp; Reconstruction 
2.1 In the short space of time since the elections our country has achieved a degree of national reconciliation, unity and stability which are remarkable, and which many thought impossible. 
2.2 Our successful political transition puts us in a strong position to accelerate the reconstruction and development of our country? 
2.3 In the Reconstruction &amp; Development Programme we have found a basis to unite all our people and harness all our energies towards a common goal. The RDP is an all-encompassing programme for the transformation of our country in order to address the legacy of apartheid. 
2.4 The success of this programme depends on a partnership of every sphere of society: government; business; labour; communities and non-governmental organisations. 
3 The role of the public service 
3.1 The public service in general, and your department in particular, have a crucial role to play in making 
the goals of reconstruction and development a reality. 
3.2 The policies of the past brought division and duplication, fragmentation and inefficiency in government and in the use of our country's national resources. They also left us with a body of public servants which was unrepresentative of our society. 
3.3 In the past months departments in central government and the provinces have faced up to the task of re-organising and restructuring themselves in order to meet the new objectives which our society has set itself, and to conduct themselves in ways which match the ideals of our democracy. 
3.4 This transformation requires every institution to take a critical look at itself. We need to ask: what kind of Public Service should we strive to create so that government is able to meet the challenges of our new non-racial, non-sexist, democratic country. 
4 Transforming the public service 
4.1 There are a number of aspects to this process, some of which you have been discussing this morning 
4.2 Internal restructuring and reorganisation 
The restructuring and transformation of departments will bring a public service whose personnel reflect the composition of our society. It will mean integrating the various separate departments created under apartheid, and, where necessary, rationalising and restructuring to ensure efficient use of resources. 
Under the guidance of the Public Service Commission, a good start has been made in addressing these issues. Perhaps we have not moved as fast as we might have hoped at the outset, but the good will which exists on all sides and constructive negotiations should provide a solid foundation from which to proceed. 
Affirmative action, of which development and training are essential parts, is needed to rectify the imbalances in racial as well as gender composition. It is aimed at redressing wrongs, not creating new ones. It is intended to ensure that all those who were disadvantaged under apartheid - particularly Africans, Indians, Coloured people and women of all groups - are able to contribute to the maximum of their potential. Like democracy, it is an opportunity to lay a sound basis for reconciliation and transformation. It will help us achieve a stronger, more efficient and effective public service, better able to address the needs of all the people of our country. 
The recent successful negotiations with the public service trade unions on this issue should lay the basis for moving forward in a way that addresses many of the fears which people have had. In this regard government is committed to developing an environment that is co-operative rather than adversarial, to ensure stability in the public service. A public service that serves all the people 
4.3 A public service that serves all the people 
The public service needs to be transformed so that it is better able to serve all the people of our country. In the past government departments were organised to achieve apartheid ends and were used as instruments of an unjust and discriminatory system. Now departments should be seen as serving the interests of all the people of South Africa. 
4.4 A public service which is innovative and democratic. 
The public service needs to be re-oriented. This should bring new and innovative approaches to policy processes. One of the most encouraging developments since our democratic government was established, is the move towards open discussion of policy and of how to implement programmes. Consultation and consensus of all role-players is central to this approach. 
This should become the normal way of addressing issues, not least because it sets free the energies of every sector of society. The creativity and initiative of government employees have been stifled for too long. 
5 Change may be difficult, but it need not be feared 
5.1 There is much to be done and many changes are necessary. 
5.2 Ek is bewus, na aanleiding van `n dokument wat onlangs deur u direkteur-generaal aan my voorgele is, dat die departemente van vervoer, nes ander staatsdepartemente en provinsiale administrasies, onderweg is na die doelwitte waarna ek verwys het. Met die geskiedenis van die eerste maande van die oorgangstyd agter ons, ondervind baie mense wat die verandering gevrees het, dat hulle vrese begin afneem. Die spoke van onbekende gevare het verander in die alledaagse werklikheid van 'n land verenig rondom die strewe na gemeenskaplike doelwitte. 
5.3 Vir mense in die staatsdiens le daar miskien nog `n moelike tyd voor. Die omvorming van die staatsdiens is steeds onderweg, maar u hoef nie hierdie veranderinge te vrees nie. Soos ons politieke oorgang self, sal 'n toestand uiteindelik bereik word waaroor ons almal bly sal wees. 
5.4 As deel van die staatsdiens, is dit u rol om lewe te gee aan die Heropbou- en Ontwikkelingsprogram, `n belangrike een. U kan direk hydra tot die bereik van 'n beter lewe vir almal in ons land.</body></text></speech>