<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1995-07-09">09 July 1995</date><text><term key="1565" /><body>Master of Ceremonies; 
Leaders of the Hindu community; 
Distinguished Guests; 
Fellow South Africans. 
For our country, and for me personally, today's event is a fulfilment of a long-cherished hope. Here, on our soil, are gathered together members of one of South Africa's proudest communities, at last able as free people to welcome fellow Hindus from across the world as their guests in a democratic South Africa. 
The joy of sharing this moment with you is all the greater for knowing that Hindus from so many countries are present. It is a particular honour to be able to welcome such eminent swamis and sages. Your participation in the World Hindu Conference being held in Durban does honour to our new democracy. May your stay in our country be a pleasant and rewarding one. 
I would like to congratulate the organisers of today's event. You have given us all a rare opportunity to participate in a moment of great historical significance. 
Dear friends; 
The strength and the richness of Hinduism has made it one of the world's oldest religions. It has endured because it has been able to give succour and guidance to its followers in all ages and all circumstances, wherever they may be. Human civilisation is immeasurably enriched by its vision and the values it which it inspires. 
Nowhere are these things more vividly demonstrated than in South Africa. Our land is graced by temples, altars and shrines built by the indentured labourers who first brought Hinduism to these shores and those who followed them. They testify to the indomitable spirit with which they sustained community and religion under adverse circumstances. 
The nurturing of Hinduism in South Africa has been woven into the struggle for freedom and justice. The HIndu community has given our nation some of its most revered leaders, amongst them Mahatma Gandhi, Dr. Monty Naicker, Mr. Nana Sita and many others. In the past several Hindu leaders were in the forefront of the struggle against oppression. Today they represent our people as a whole in Parliament and the provincial governments, leading the transformation of our society in order to address the legacy of apartheid. 
Our vision of a free and equitable society at peace with itself is also to be found in the core values of Hinduism: tolerance, peace and unity. These values, as expressed in the pronouncements and writings of Ghandi and Nehru, had a profound and lasting influence on our liberation movement, and on my own thinking. 
The relevance of these values to our society has never been greater than in this time of nation building and national reconciliation. 
If we have been able to aspire to the accolade of the 'Rainbow Nation', it is in part because of what we have drawn from that tradition. Our rich tapestry of many cultures and religions is protected constitutionally. But more importantly, tolerance and respect for the values and the culture of others are written in the hearts of our people, and enshrined in the practices of our government, institutions and parties. 
As one recent token of the seriousness of this commitment, our public broadcaster has now acknowledged the place of Hinduism in the mainstream of our national life. 
Dear friends and compatriots; 
Our country, freed at last from apartheid and minority rule, is going through a profound transformation. It is only natural that this process of change which brings much hope and promise, also has its share of anxieties. 
As a nation we have set ourselves a bold challenge indeed. We are seeking to turn centuries of division and fear into unity and peace, and to do so in a matter of years. We are striving to transform our society in order to address the legacy of apartheid. 
The progress we have made in the short space of a year has surpassed all expectations. Time and again the prophets of doom have been confounded. The reason for our success thus far is the powerful urge towards consensus which is coursing through our society, cutting across all the old divisions which apartheid imposed upon us. That is what gives us reason to be confident that any problems we do face will find solutions through negotiation and in the interests of all. 
The challenge we all face is to work together on the common ground that unites us, rather than allowing ourselves to by divided by the differences which may exist, which are much smaller. 
This means joining hands to create a better life for all South Africans, by making a success of the reconstruction and development programme. 
It means ensuring that the opportunities now opening up should benefit all those - particularly from the Indian, Coloured and African communities - who were excluded and held back by the discriminatory practices of apartheid. 
We should all be alert to false claims, by those seeking to perpetuate the divisions and imbalances of the past, that the government's policy of affirmative action is intended to benefit only one section of society. Sometimes it does happen that people are refused employment or opportunity in this way, whether it is at work, in business or in education. We wish to state categorically that this is contrary to the policy of the Government of National Unity, and the African National Congress. 
It is only by unleashing the full potential of all our people that South Africa will become the prosperous and peaceful nation to which we all aspire. 
Everything we are striving to do requires the full and active participation of citizens in their communities, working together with government. 
That applies also to safety and security, which the government has put amongst its highest priorities. Those who break the law must know that they will be caught, and that they will face the full force of the law. 
As part of the government's campaign to deal with crime it launched the Community Safety Plan. Even in the first few months it has achieved remarkable successes in the targeted areas. The secret of that success has been the support and co-operation which communities are giving to the police, and we appeal to all religious organisations to throw their weight behind such co-operation. 
These advances and the unmistakable signs of economic growth which we are experiencing, have become possible with democracy and our growing national unity. We have been able to forge a consensus on economic policies which create an environment of opportunities for business to flourish. Our first year of government has allowed the plans for transformation to be put in place, and we are now shifting the emphasis to visible change. 
What we started with the elections in April last year, is only half done. It must be completed in November this year with the first democratic local government elections. It is when communities at the local level have the power to govern themselves, that we can ensure the effective implementation of the plans for reconstruction and development. 
It is there, at the local level, that the most decisive work must be done to heal the wounds which apartheid inflicted on our society. The Indian community is well-placed to contribute to this process, especially in this province of KwaZulu-Natal, and above all in Durban. 
The experience of the first year of democratic government has removed the basis of the fears which gave credence to divisive ways of thinking about the diversity of our people. Our diversity is now a source of strength, the strength of one South African nation of many cultures and religions but united to a common destiny. 
All cultures and religions now enjoy equal respect, without preference. For the first time in our history this equality and freedom is enshrined in our constitution. 
No longer do our communities need to think of themselves as a minorities threatened by the majority. Assured that their culture is safe and their religion protected, they are free to think of themselves as part of the South African nation. They can be confident that their traditions are admired and respected. 
The conditions are also ripe for all religions to join together in a common commitment to harmony, peace and national reconciliation. Uniting around these noble values that are common to our different faiths, will help to safeguard our new freedom and consolidate our democracy. It will also help us avoid the kinds of religious tensions which are being experienced in many other parts of the world. 
Hinduism has a special role to play in nation-building and reconciliation, reconstruction and development. As we are gathered here today, from across our land and from communities across the world, let us dedicate ourselves to a vision for the twenty-first century. It is a vision based on tolerance and unity, an equitable distribution of resources, on peace and friendship in this our South African nation, and between the nations of the world. 
May peace be with you. 
God bless you.</body></text></speech>