Our country is today a democracy in the complete sense of the word. The people of South Africa have spoken. They have shown their resolve to unite our nation and together build a better life for all. The large turnout during the local government elections and the overwhelming support for the African National Congress is a victory for the whole of South Africa. I am deeply humbled and grateful for the way in which government, and especially the African National Congress as the majority party, has been strengthened to carry out our task to make our country a better place for all its’ people. All South Africans have shown a remarkable maturity and took the lead in breaking the racial moulds of the past. 
Die kiesers van die Wes-Kaap het a besondere voorbeeld aan ons almal gestel. 
Applause and laughter 
(That’s what I told them to do, you know.) 
Deur die mag van die stembrief is ons besig om die verlede vir eens en vir altyd te begrawe. 
My exhilaration is only marred by the sad upset of the vote of the people of KwaZulu-Natal and the Cape Town Metropolitan Area, and other areas. I give them my assurance that they will soon be able to fully share in our joy. There is no doubt that democracy will be strengthened by their vote. My sympathy also goes to those who have registered but were seemingly not placed on the voter’s role. As the majority party, the ANC assures you that the electoral authorities will build the professional capacity required to minimize such problems in the future. 
I congratulate every local government representative who has been elected. A great responsibility now rests on your shoulders to ensure that you reciprocate the trust of the people by immediately establishing efficient and accountable structures of government. Now is the time to roll up your sleeves and work with the community to ensure that we build a better life where we live. 
As ANC councillors, you must not ask who voted for the ANC, but unite and serve all the people of our country. I call on all South Africans to work together with their councillors. The people of South Africa have spoken, to ourselves and to the whole world. We have declared that we have taken responsibility for our own future. 
The rainbow nation of South Africa is coming of age. Let’s get down to work. Let’s make it happen where we live.