1. Introduction 

1.1 It is with much excitement and optimism that I stand before you today, excited at being among the people who ensured the ANC was placed at the head of both the National and Eastern Cape government. With the local government elections just around the corner we are entering a crucial stage in the process of democratisation. 

1.2 Through an ANC-led national and provincial government, the process of nation building has begun. We are moving towards building a better life for all. With the ANC in local government, together we can make sure that this happens for all the people of the Eastern Cape. 

2. A START HAS BEEN MADE 

2.1 The ANC-led Eastern Cape Government has made an impressive start towards alleviating much of the poverty and unemployment that plagued this province during the apartheid years. The Presidential lead projects which have begun in Duncan Village and Port Elizabeth are aimed at dealing with some of these problems. 

2.2 But this is only a start. ANC-led democratic local councils will ensure that the process of building a better life where you live, will happen. 

2.3 In this province you have also started the difficult task of blending together three civil services with different cultures and methods of operating. This has understandably resulted in a measure of insecurity and anxiety. 

2.4 The Eastern Cape province relies heavily on its civil servants for the delivery of many essential services. The ANC recognises the importance of its civil servants in the successful implementation of RDP projects. The ANC has no plans to leave our civil servants out in the cold. We need you to work together with us towards building a better life for all of our communities. 

3. THE IMPORTANCE OF LOCAL GOVERNMENT 

3.1 Last year's election brought democratic government to the nation and the provinces. By voting in the elections of November 1st, every local community will get a voice in government. 

3.2 Through local government, communities will have the power to work with the ANC-led national government to make the RDP work for them. Our candidates in the ANC are working closely with the people in their areas to put power where it works best - in the communities. 

3.3 Through democratic local councils we can build a better life for our families and our communities, where we live. 

4. YOU CAN RELY ON THE ANC 

4.1 The councillors you elect in the local government elections will become the main agents of change in your communities. When you choose your candidates, they should be people you can rely on. 

4.2 They must be people who understand your problems, care about your future, and know how to listen. 

4.3 ANC candidates are people from your area, who have always worked for a better life for the people in your community. As ANC councillors, they will make sure that the resources of local government are used for the benefit of all in the Eastern Cape. 

4.4 ANC candidates, and the ANC as an organization stand apart from other candidates and political parties, as the only party who knows how to listen. In the ANC we understand that democracy means empowering communities. The ANC does not simply make decisions for you. The ANC involves you in deciding what you want, and what is best for you. 

5. CHALLENGES FACING THE EASTERN CAPE PROVINCE 

5.1 The ANC recognises that this province suffers, perhaps more acutely than others, from apartheid's legacy of poverty and under development, unemployment and deprivation. 

5.2 It is crucial that the economy of the Eastern Cape Province is boosted in order to create more jobs. Local economic development requires a vision for the local economy. Only, you, the people of the Eastern Cape, can develop that vision through a partnership of government, business, labour and community, all working together. 

5.3 Through working together with all sectors of the communities of this province, both rural and urban, development can occur. It is only right that rural development claims its fair share of attention. 

5.4 I am gravely concerned about the escalating crime rate in this province. Uplifting the socio-economic conditions of the Eastern Cape will go some way towards reducing crime. But we must act firmly now against the unacceptable levels of crime. 

5.5 The number of weapons in the hands of civilians in South Africa, and including this province, is one of the sources of violence. Government is taking steps to combat this. The recent barbaric attack on tourists in Lusikisiki must spur us into immediate action. Our country and our communities must be safe for all our people and our guests. 

5.5 In order to root out the crime in our communities we will all have to work together. Building unity and working together to build a more secure and stable environment is the key to combating crime. 

5.6 Much has been said about tensions over the place of traditional leaders in the democracy we are establishing. There is no reason why traditional leaders cannot work together with elected communities, and we are confident that a solution will be formed to the problems. In this regard we trust that a meeting next week between traditional leaders and the ANC's NEC will bear fruit. 

6. WORKING TOGETHER 

6.1 Community involvement is the answer to successfully tackling the poverty, crime and lack of development that has for so long been a burden of the Eastern Cape Province. 

6.2 It is through unity and working together that you, the people of the Eastern Cape will be able to rise to the challenges that face you. 

6.3 The plans that the ANC has starred to implement come from the people. Together we have started to change South Africa for the better. Together, we can make these plans succeed, we can build a better life where we live. 

6.4 Let us come together as communities to fight crime. Let us come together to identify our urgent needs and make proposals to government. Together, we have the power to make the RDA' a resounding success. Together, we can build a better life. Together we can make it happen where we live.