<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1995-10-12">12 October 1995</date><text><term key="1260" /><body>Ladies and Gentlemen of the media; 

Distinguished business people; 

Trustees of the Children's Fund; 

Ladies and gentlemen. 

Today, marks a special moment for our Children's Fund. 

Just five months ago the formal launch of the Fund took it from the realm of planning and commitment to that of an 

active agency. 

At its launch the Fund set itself the task of being a catalyst in innovative and inspiring initiatives to break the shackles of poverty binding our youth, and to unlock the promise of opportunity. 

The initiative we are announcing today is just such a project, with a special focus on youth in detention. It opens a new path, breaking the mould within which our society has hitherto treated young convicted persons. It will enable them to help themselves to participate fully in society - through appropriate education and life-skills training aligned to the world of work. 

What is particularly inspiring, is that people from all walks of life are involved - business, labour, political parties and community organisations, along with government. 

Five major partners are involved. 

First, there is the Private Sector Initiative formed four years ago in order to make a significant intervention in education. I would like to acknowledge and pay special tribute to the 14 major companies that make up the PSI. They are: AECI; Anglo American &amp; De Beers; Barlows; Caltex; FNB; Gencor; JCI; SA Breweries; Sankorp companies; Sanlam; Sasol; Shell; Southern Life and Standard Bank. 

These companies, represented here today by their executive directors and the Chairman of the PSI, Mike Rosholt, are household names in the business world, although few people realise how much they are doing quietly in the area of democratisation and upliftment. 

Collectively, they are providing some R30 million for this pilot project alone. One of the companies in the Sankorp Group - Murray &amp; Roberts - is also providing classrooms at some R400 000 below market value. Amdev, as the project managers, will ensure that local contractors and entrepreneurs can participate in the project and that local people are employed in it. 

A second partner is the Joint Educational Trust, itself a shining example of an alliance between business, labour, community organisations and political parties. JET and its education allies will provide the curriculum, co-ordinate the training of teachers and evaluate the programme in its first years. They will fund this element and provide financial management for the initiative. 

Thirdly, the Rand Afrikaans University is designing the development curriculum and the management model of the Youth Development Centre, drawing on its extensive involvement in community development and its experience in combining research and development programmes. 

Fourthly, the Government, through the Minister of Correctional Services, will work in close collaboration with the private sector over the first two or three years of the project and in time inherit the operation. The plan is for government to replicate the model throughout the country, once it is fully developed and tested.. 

Last, but not least, is the Patron of the project our Children's Fund, which will own the property through an Educational Trust. 

So the Fund is indeed fulfilling its promise to build creative alliances and mobilise greater resources to produce more effective results. 

It is opening opportunities that have been denied. It is helping to release the potential of our youth to assume a major role in contributing to economic growth and to peace and harmony in our communities. In doing so, it will restore their dignity and pride in living. Through the Youth Development Centre it will provide a catalyst for young detained persons to take their rightful and productive place in the world of work. 

It is not my task to detail the workings of this pilot project in Newcastle. That will be done by those with me here today, men and women of great repute who possess a wealth of experience in these matters 

Suffice it to say that the project stands as a model of how different elements of our various endeavours support and promote each other. The project combines the fulfilment of our obligation to young people; nation-building through a partnership to bring change; and the creation of jobs and opportunities. 

In encouraging us all to take responsibility for bringing about change, it initiates a new path which will help change both those who make it and the future of our country. 

I thank you.</body></text></speech>