Chairperson; 
Fellow South Africans 
I am very glad to have the opportunity to meet with you here this morning. It as at gatherings of this kind that I appreciate anew the wonderful thing we have wrought in our country: a coming together of people of all backgrounds, opinions and beliefs. We should all be grateful and proud that we have experienced this in our lifetime. I am proud. 
I would like to talk, this morning, about what we can do together to deepen the New Patriotism that is emerging in our country. 
Our country has been deeply divided for many years, and we still experience the legacy of those divisions every day. The role of the Reconstruction and Development Program is to address that legacy in order to build a better life for all. It will take time but it is underway. We have made a good start in building a better life for all. 
But there is also another kind of division that runs deep in our society - an alienation experienced by many of our citizens and communities both from each other, and from government itself. 
It is only natural that the experience of bad and corrupt government, felt by all of us in different ways, should have bred in many people a mistrust of the very concept of government itself. We should recognise this mistrust also as a legacy of our past. Without claiming that ANC members are incapable of wrongdoing, the ANC has committed itself to open, transparent and accountable democracy - to a form of government that contains all the necessary checks and balances in order to preserve and protect democracy and human rights. 
A fully functioning democracy is one in which people participate, working together as part of a single nation, making their contribution - great or small - towards the well-being of the nation as a whole. 
It is the movement towards this goal that is nourishing the New Patriotism. This is more than just pride in ones country. It is a tangible patriotism in which everyone plays her or his part, working together in building the New South Africa. It draws vitality too from the progress we have made in overcoming the divisions of the past. Across our society South Africans feel liberated from artificial constraints and have entered a world of wider relationships as equals with their fellow South African. 
Ons praat van 'n reenboognasie. Maar vir 'n reenboog om to bestaan hang af van die interaksie en onderahankikheid van al die verskillende kleure. Dit hang af van elkeen van die verskillende dele van die geheel om die wonderlike voile spektrum te skep. 
Een van die belangrikste en effektiefste wyses wat ons, ons stemme kan laat hoor is op plaaslikevlak. 
Twee jaar gelede in die nasionale verkiesing het Suid-Afrikaners gestem vir vryheid en 'n beter lewe vir almal. Ons het inderdaad 'n goeie begin gemaak. Nou se ons: kom ons laat dit ook hier gebeur in Kaapstad. Ten einde dit 'n werklikheid te maak moet ons goeie kandidate verkies wat ons respekteer en vertrou. 
As deel van die wonderlike reenboog moet ons natuurlik altyd onthou dat ons werklike glorie 18 in wat ons saam bereik - as 'n land en sy mense. 
Ons het, sedert die ANC die leidende party in die Regering van Nasionale Eenheid geword het, altyd gepoog om ander se standpunte in aanmerking te neem. Ons het dan ook 'n Kommissie daaar gestel wat sal verseker dat eenheid en versoening in ons land nagestreef word. Ons het die Springbokke ons eie gemaak - as rugbyspan en as simbool wat in die verlede deur so baie Suid-Afrikaners verwerp is, maar nou ondersteun word. Ons het indringende gesprekke gehad net elke opinie groep - selfs in die ver regse groepe en ons het aandagtig geluister na wat hulle te se gehad het. 
U mag moontlik clink dat die stappe slegssimbolies van card is. Tog is hulle van geweldige belang en ek sal baie graag wil sien dat elke Suid¬Afrikaner uit eie oortuiging hierdie stappe moet voortsit. Ek wil 'n spesiale oproep maak aan u almal om verdraagdsaamheid aan die dag te lé wanneer u dinge in die gesig staar wat u bang of verbouereerd maak. Korn ons gee mekaar die voordeel van die twyfel. Baie van ons is nog vreemdelinge vir mekaar en ons moet mekaar behoorlik leer ken. 
Often, when we talk about a vision for the future, we do not do so in practical ways. When we think about building the future we should think of those who will inherit that future. In other words, we need to think of our children and our grandchildren, who trust us to take care of the future for them. The choices and decisions which we make will profoundly affect their lives. 
This is why we must consider very carefully where on the ballot paper we make our mark in the coming elections. Every time we vote, we take an important step towards building, not only our own world, but the world we will leave to those that come after us. 
I, of course, will advise you to vote for the ANC. But I do not urge you to vote for the ANC because I am the leader of that party. I urge you to vote for the ANC because I believe it is the only organisation in this country that has the policies, the vision and the determination to unite all South Africans to work together to make democracy a living reality and to build a better life for all. 
I greet you all and I wish you all well. Although I am obliged to travel a great deal, my thoughts are very much with this city and this province which hosted me and my colleagues over 26 years. Like you I was left behind last November. On 29 May it will be my turn to cast my vote for democratic local government. 
'n Beter Lewe vir Almal: 
Kom ons laat dit gebeur ook hier in Kaapstad!