Ke a le dumedisa! Ngiyanibingelela! 
Ri perile! Goeienaand! 
Ndi madekwana! 
It is a pleasure for me to share with you this dawn of a new era in South African Radio. I extend my hands to join you in saying: Kusile! Bosele! 
In these times of rapid change, people sometimes ask: do we need a public broadcaster like the SABC? What with the serious backlogs in housing, education, health and other services! 
To me and our democratic government, the answer is clear: Quite simply the public broadcaster offers us the opportunity to be agents of change. It is the guarantee of high quality and diverse programmes for all. It caters to all of us because it belongs to all of us. 
The public broadcaster gives us information, education and entertainment in all official languages. It has the potential to provide news we can trust. It helps to promote local music, cultural activity and different religions without discrimination. It caters for young and old, rich and poor, black and white, in every province of the country. 
Without it our lives would be a lot emptier. 
The last few years have seen bold initiatives to transform the SABC into a true broadcaster of the people. 
This has not always been easy; and it is not yet fully complete. Much more needs to be done to ensure that the SABC becomes a true independent and credible broadcaster, not manipulated by forces opposed to democracy - or anyone else for that matter. 
I am confident that the SABC is on its way: to ensure that it serves the public and guarantee their right to know. 
As we can see and hear tonight, nowhere is this more possible than on SABC Radio. 
With its 16 different stations, SABC Radio has an audience of 18-million people; and it caters to all language and cultural communities. 
SABC Radio alone has the ability to speak to all our citizens. 
Many listeners are the poorest South Africans. They live in distant, under-developed areas without electricity and in many cases unable to read. But that small box, running on batteries, receiving SABC and other broadcasts keeps them in touch with their country and the world. It keeps them in touch with parliament, with the Truth Commission, with the United Nations and indeed with the FNB stadium and Loftus Versfeld! 
SABC Radio therefore has a great responsibility. 
I am confident that with this re-launch, the SABC is once more signalling its commitment to change; its pledge to promote the interests of South Africa; and its promise to each and every one of the millions of listeners. 
To all those assembled here tonight, and to all of you at home or travelling or anywhere else following this historic rebirth on your radio set, I wish to say a special hello! 
This celebration is for you. These radio stations belong to you. You are SABC Radio. 
Enjoy the evening!