I am excited to be here today, in Khayelitsha, on the eve of the local government election. It is here that we have some of our most loyal supporters. It is here that democratic local government has so much work to do in helping address the legacy of apartheid. 
A Better Life for All 
1. In April 1994 the people of South Africa voted for democracy and a better life for all. The majority chose the ANC because it has fought for the rights of all South Africans for generations and because it embodied their vision for a new South Africa. 
2. In November last year most of the country voted to set up democratic local government for the first time. Again, the majority voted for the ANC because the government, under the ANC's leadership had made a start in improving the lives of millions of ordinary people. 
3. Now, across the country, communities are working through their new democratic councils to make a better live happen where they live. 
Now it's our turn 
1. The voters in the Cape and in rural areas of this province, along with the voters of KwaZulu/Natal, were left out of the November elections. Now its our turn. On 29 May we will at last have the chance to voter for democratic local councils. 
2. Democratically elected councils will give people the power to decide what is best for their own communities and give them a voice which higher levels of government must hear. Local councils will unify communities and remain accountable to those they serve. 
The ANC - A party and candidate you can rely on 
1. Our candidate here in this ward is Booi Mawethu. I have complete confidence in this candidate, because he is a disciplined member of the ANC. He is committed to following the organisation's policies, to the goal making a better life here where we live, here in Khayelitsha. 
2. The key to realising these goals is the election of strong ANC-led councils. The ANC is the only party with a history of bringing together all South Africans to work together to improve the quality of life. 
3. ANC candidates are from the community and understand the community's needs. They will remain accountable to you even after the election, because that is the tradition of the ANC. 
4. It is because of the ANC's commitment to democracy and because it has united most of this country around the same goals, that we have all been able to make a start to achieving our goals. 
5. And that is why it is important for everyone who shares those goals to unite behind the ANC candidates. Those who have worked with the ANC in the past but are now standing as independents will slow down the community's achievement of its goals, and strengthen the hand of those who do not share our dream of a united South Africa. 
6. So I urge you to vote for the ANC candidates, the ones who have the ANC symbol next to their name. 
Community power means community responsibility 
1. In voting for ANC candidates you will choose people who are committed to working for community's to have a say in their own lives - and for community's to take responsibility for the management of the services they use. The ANC is committed to the spirit of Masakhane. At the same time as working to improve the services to our communities, we must also pay t for the services that are received. Every drop of water costs money to bring to you. People must work to get that water into the pipes, to lay the pipes. And these people must be paid. If people do not pay for services, how are those who are still waiting for them ever to get them?. 
2. Houses have been transferred to people without payment, land is being transferred to people of this community so that they own their land. All they have to pay is service charge, no rent. In paying the rent you will contribute to the betterment of this community. 
We have made a start. - We are proud of our achievements 
1. The ANC-led government's plans to change our country have been bringing improvements to millions across the country. through school-feeding schemes; free health care for pregnant mothers and young children; clean water and electricity for hundreds of thousands long denied those basic rights. 
2. The facilities in the areas where people live have also begun to change, and Khayelitsha is no exception. For example 
- The shopping Centre in site B has been developed with RDP funding, creating employment and providing a facility for this community. 
- The Michael Mpongwana Hospital to be opened in September and the clinics that have been opened and upgraded in Khayelitsha will bring health-care for members of this community will result from. Money has been allocated for road-building and the building of the magistrates court. 
We have a plan. 
1. The ANC fought to have Khayelitsha included in the Tygerberg Sub structure so that its tax-base and its well- developed infrastructure can be used for the benefit of all. Now we must unite behind the ANC to work in the Tygerberg to develop this area into a community we are all proud to live in. 
2. When Khayelitsha is integrated into the Metro, it can become part of a united city, if the ANC is the majority party. The ANC has a plan to develop the entire metro. Areas like Khayelitsha will be fully integrated into the whole life of the city, so that there will be development that brings work, business and recreation facilities close to where you live. 
3. We have a plan for transport that will provide safe, affordable transport for this community. We have made a major breakthrough this week in securing an end to taxi violence and we hope that this agreement will make taxi travel safe. 
Making it happen in Khayelitsha 
The people of Khayelitsha are ready to take control of what happens in this area, and to share with government the responsibility to bring about change and build a better life. 
Vote for the ANC candidates with the ANC symbol next to their names. 
A better life for all 
Let's make it happen in Khayelitsha! 
Now it’s our turn!