<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1996-05-25">25 May 1996</date><text><term key="1304" /><body>I am honoured by the Creation of this Senior Teaching Cathedra through which students from the esteemed Higher Institute of Mining and Metallurgy of Moa could study and learn, not only from the struggle of the African people, but also from their achievements, Cuba has proved, throughout the struggle for freedom in South Africa as well as in the process of democratisation and reconstruction to be a valuable friend and supporter. For that we are immensely grateful. 
Let me assure you, that the great majority of South Africans will never forget those who stood by us in the darkest years of our struggle. Along with the majority of humanity, we in South Africa, are determined to be active participants in the noble efforts for a just world order. 
As in Cuba, education and the training of the youth, are also a priority of the South African Government, as the youth are not only the leaders of the future, but also the essence and heart of our young democracy. Through the creation of this Senior Teaching Cathedra Cuban students will be able to learn about South Africa's difficult past. But we trust that above all they will learn about South Africa's future and the great potential that exists. 
In pursuit of a better future for both our nations, Cuba and South Africa should, as in the past, co-operate and assist each other in all areas of endeavour. 
We wish to record our indebtedness to Cuban hospitality. In particular, tons of thousands of young South Africans have been trained and are still in training, in Cuban schools and universities. Today, in many different fields there are many young professionals, contributing to the development of our country, who owe their skills to the generous training provided to them by Cuba- a process that must continue to our mutual benefit. 
Thank you once again for this honour and I do trust that this friendship between the peoples of South Africa and Cuba will remain and grow from strength to strength. In conclusion, I wish the Institute of Mining and Metallurgy of Moa, every success in its future endeavours. 
Nelson Mandela</body></text></speech>