<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1996-12-14">14 December 1996</date><text><term key="1332" /><body>Formation of the MK Military Veterans Association 
1. The formation of the MK Military Veterans Association is a milestone in our history. When Umkhonto we Sizwe was dissolved two years ago, the ANC decided that it should set up a home for veterans of the armed struggle. I am delighted to see that this is now happening. 
2. In this way, we are paying homage to Oliver Tambo, Joe Slovo, Moses Mabhida, Chris Hani, Malume Kotane, JB Marks, Yusuf Dadoo, Basil February and other veterans who are no longer with us. The MK veterans association has two major purposes. 
Remembering our Past 
1. The first purpose of the association is to preserve the proud history and heritage of MK. It must ensure that our nation never forgets those who fought and died for freedom. 
2. The democratic constitution I signed into law this week might have eluded our people for generations to come, had it not been for Umkhonto we Sizwe. MK was born of the need to defend our people and the desire for liberation, at a time when the Apartheid regime responded to our peaceful resistance with brute and deadly force. As soldiers of our people, you fearlessly engaged this powerful enemy, and exposed it as a colossus with feet of clay. 
3. The Veterans Association will keep alive the memory of those who fought so bravely for a just and democratic society. Through the names of its senior commanders and brave combatants like Solomon Mahlangu, Vuyisile Mini, Barney Molokoane, Ashley Kriel, Ahmed Timol and others, we will always salute the army of the people, Umkhonto we Sizwe. 
4. We look to the Veterans Association to provide suggestions on what should be done to honour our soldiers who are still buried abroad and those who fell in action on the home front. The association will also be a source of ideas for preserving and promoting the history of MK. 
Caring for our War Veterans 
1. The second purpose of this association is to champion the welfare and the needs of ex-combatants. No veteran of our liberation army and their families should ever be destitute or unable to provide their children with adequate education. 
2. Countries all over the world take care of their war veterans. South Africa did so to some extent but insufficiently. Veterans of the First and Second World Wars, for example, receive some care from the state. It is up to both MK and Apia veterans associations to see that their members receive state care and benefits. As government, a product of the sacrifices of these veterans, we will do our best to ensure that this is realised. 
3. It is also important that you establish and consolidate international finks and work with other veterans associations for world peace, social justice and a better life. 
Service Awards 
1. The Ministry of Defence has commissioned medals that recognise valour, merit and long service on the part of liberation fighters. Of these, the first to be ready, for presentation today, is the service award in three classes of 10, 20 and 30 years of service. Future ceremonies will include awards for valour and merit, so that those presently in the SANDF who once served in MK and Apia can also be duly honoured. 
2. Today, service medals will be bestowed upon generations of Umkhonto we Sizwe soldiers who sacrificed a secure life to fight for a humane society. Those who are decorated today should know that this award honours your whole-hearted commitment; your bravery and your selflessness. It celebrates your success in helping bring the era of apartheid to an end. You have done our nation and our continent proud, and you have widened the frontiers of freedom. Wear your medal with pride! 
3. As the first Commander in Chief of MK, I too will be receiving a service award. I will accept it in all humility, knowing that it recognises not the achievement of an individual, but that of our army as a whole. 
4. To the other detachments who receive awards today - the Rivonia Trialists, the Luthuli detachment, the June 16 detachment, the Madinoga detachment, the Young Lions of the eighties and others - we say: Over the years you carried the torch of the African National Congress bravely, and with dignity. Continue to do so. Work to make the MK Military Veterans Association a guardian of all who fought in the armed struggle, a force of example to the youth of today and generations to come. 
Conclusion 
1. In conclusion, I wish the Veterans Military Association every success in its endeavours. 
2. May I leave with you a few inspirational and instructional words from our dear friend comrade Chris Hani: "We have the right as Umkhonto we Sizwe to look back at our history with pride and to tell ourselves that we have really made an important contribution to the struggle for democracy, for unity, non-racialism and non-sexism in South Africa". 
That pride, and the historical reality of our pre-eminent contribution in eradicating a crime against humanity, no one can take from us! 
A better life for all - forward ever! 
Amanda! All power to the people!</body></text></speech>