Honourable Ministers; 

Chief of the South African National Defence Force and the Secretary for Defence; 

Premier of the Northwest Province; 

Officers, men and women of the National Defence Force; 

Distinguished Guests. 

With each birthday parade, one cannot but feel the welling of pride at the progress the National Defence Force is making to transform itself into a new force of a new nation. 

Tomorrow, the SANDF will be three years old: but you are up an running - a force for peace in our sub-continent and further afield; a reliable partner in the fight against crime; the sword and shield of our young democracy. 

As commander-in-Chief, it is an honour for me to once again join you in these celebrations. 

The past year has been marked by some notable achievements in our defence establishment. All this has been done in the midst of a historic challenge for the National Defence Force to redefine itself. Problems there are, and there shall always be as we build the new; but you are passing the test with flying colours. 

The adoption last year of the White Paper on Defence, after lengthy consultation, has set the stage for national consensus on our defence tasks. From this comprehensive assessment of the new strategic environment, we are now able to more clearly determine the role, the needs and the priorities of our National Defence Force. 

We also had to do this within the context of our obligations, as a nation, in the region and beyond. As South Africa's standing and contribution in international matters amplify, so will the SANDF be called upon to take part in peace support operations. The government is impressed at the speed and enthusiasm with which you have taken up this new challenges. 

Our contribution to Southern Africa's preparedness for this task was reflected in the peace-support operational training at our army battle school. Above all, a contingent of the SANDF has just taken part in a multinational joint peace support exercise in Zimbabwe, whose forces have considerable experience in this role. 

As a new partner in these operations, we have to learn and learn fast; and we have to gear ourselves with deliberate speed to respond to the call of the international community. 

As the White Paper clearly outlines, we place a great premium on maximum-operation with other states, especially in Southern Africa. A new paradigm of collective security is emerging, characterised by co-operation among SADC countries in the spirit of mutual respect and equality. Hand-in-hand with our neighbours, we shall always seek non-violence means to resolve conflicts; and to ensure sufficient deterrence as a means of self-defence. 

Our contribution to Southern Africa's preparedness for this task was reflected in the peace-support operational training at our army battle school. Above all, a contingent of the SANDF has just taken part in a multinational joint peace support exercise in Zimbabwe, whose forces have considerable experience in this role. 

As a new partner in these operations, we have to learn and learn fast; and we have to gear ourselves with deliberate speed to respond to the call of the international community. 

As the White paper clearly outlines, we place a great premium on maximum co-operation with other states, especially in Southern Africa. A new paradigm of collective security is emerging, characterised by co-operation among SADC countries in the spirit of mutual respect and equality. Hand-in-hand with our neighbours, we shall always seek non-violence means to resolve conflicts; and to ensure sufficient deterrence as a means of self-defence. 

Such deterrence demands that we have to maintain a credible defence capability. And we know too keenly that military capability cannot be turned on and off like a tap. It is therefore essential for us to maintain a balanced and sustainable nucleus in the form of a core defence component. 

I have been kept fully briefed on the progress you are making with regard to the Defence Review. It was to be expected that, because the nation shares a common loyalty to the country, consensus would be reached on options for force design. And I am confident that the discussions on human resource implications will reach their conclusion without any major hitches. 

Throughout the year, the SANDF has again provided a great deal of support to the Police Service in the national battle against crime and violence and in the preservation of public order. 

For this purpose large numbers of troops have been deployed in back-up roles in various parts of the country. Currently, an even larger contingent of the SANDF is taking part in the high-density anti-crime operation in support of the police. And, discussions are under way to optimise this involvement, within the parameters laid down in the constitution. 

Other defence force members have been engaged in border protection, to combat the threats posed by illegal immigrants, gun running and drug smuggling. The Medical Service has also been of invaluable assistance to the Department of Health in national inoculation programmes, the staffing of emergency service and in the training of medical personnel. The Navy has been critical in protecting our waters and our marine resources. 

In all these support functions; in building the defence force into a legitimate sword and shield of our young democracy; and in projects such as the service corps, you are taking full and active part in the reconstruction and development of our country. 

Of course, this has to be done within the context of meagre resources. That is why the ministry and the department should be congratulated for the professional manner in which they have sought to address the real problem of a reduced defence budget. We are convinced that our defence machine has the capability to do better with less. 

This is reflected in the creative restructuring of the command centre; and the proposals for lower levels of the force to be implemented over the next three years. This will not only bring financial savings; but it will also ensure that we have an efficient and effective National Defence Force. 

Naturally, this process will have human resource implications. This is an area of prime concern to every member. The question being asked is: "how will this affect me?" Clearly, implementation will be governed by the final force design and structures flowing from the Defence Review. 

However, although the personnel component of the defence establishment will be significantly less than the present strength, we are obliged to ensure that cutbacks do not have an adverse impact on its operational capabilities. And we are duty-bound to seek ways in which individuals affected can be re-deployed within government; or acquire other skills to operate in the private sector. 

This year, the seventy fifth anniversary of the Navy's founding, is a significant milestone in its history. Earlier this month, we were honoured by the most impressive international fleet review, demonstrating not only the strategic position we occupy but also that we have the potential to become an important international naval power. 

I once more offer my sincere congratulations to the Navy and the defence force as a whole. As with other arms of service, the Navy deserves modern equipment, in line with our national and international obligations in the modern world. 

This year's Defence Force Day and Parade is being hosted by the North West Command an the city of Potchefstroom. I heartily commend the efficiency with which the events of the day have been organised and thank the City Council and members of the public for your co-operation. I also applaud the members on parade for your professional display. 

I am very pleased to hear that throughout the past three years, there has been a first-class relationship between the Command, the City Council and the Premier and Government of the province. 

In conclusion, I wish to assure all members of the SANDF that my Government and I will continue to give you our fullest support in the execution of your duties; as you grow and mature to become a balanced, modern and technologically advanced force; as you become more representative of the population; and as you promote equal opportunities and gender equality in all spheres of military activity. 

It is anticipated that, in the year ahead, some of you may be involved in peace support operations beyond our borders. Whatever you are called upon to do, I am confident that each assignment will be carried out in a thoroughly efficient and professional manner. Wherever you are, be assured that you have the nation's love and support. 

I also wish to take this opportunity to express my admiration to the families of our servicemen and women. Their constant support and encouragement to both our full-time and part-time members is worthy of praise beyond measure. 

Their support and that of all South Africans is a deserved accolade to a force of loyal and committed men and women; citizens ready to serve their nation and their country in times of joy and in times of war. 

I wish each member of the National Defence Force every success in the challenges that lie ahead. I know that you will always earn the pride of the nation in the great tradition of your military calling. 

I thank you.