<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1997-08-20">20 August 1997</date><text><term key="1458" /><body>This version has two additional paragraphs that are not the SA Government Information website.
President Mandela will be visiting Switzerland officially on 3 September 1997 at the invitation of Swiss President Arnold Koller. The President will be accompanied on the official leg of his visit by Minister SV Tshwete, Deputy Minister AGH Pahad and Deputy Minister P Mlambo-Ngcuka. 
During the visit, President Mandela will hold discussions with President Koller, the Swiss Vice- President and Foreign Minister, Mr Flavio Cotti, as well as other members of the Swiss Federal Council (Cabinet) and the Swiss business community. 
Following his official visit to Berne, the President will travel to Lausanne on 4 September 1997 to join Deputy President Mbeki and members of the Cabinet Sub-Committee for the 2004 Olympic Bid for Cape Town's final presentation to the International Olympic Committee. The President will depart for South Africa on 5 September 1997. The announcement of the successful city to host the 2004 Olympic Games will be made later that same day. 
South Africa and Switzerland enjoy excellent relations dating back several decades and Switzerland has afforded South Africa special status on its foreign policy agenda as the most important area for Swiss interests outside Europe. Switzerland is also one of South Africa's main economic partners. Direct foreign investment from Switzerland has grown steadily, particularly since 1994 with the value of new investments approaching R1 billion. In 1996, South African exports to Switzerland amounted to R2.94 billion and imports from Switzerland amounted to R 2.94 billion. Switzerland is very supportive of the development process in South Africa and has contributed close to R 300 million to the realization of the aims of the Reconstruction and Development Programme since 1994. Most recently, Switzerland donated an amount of CHF 500 000 (approximately R 1.51 million) to the Truth and Reconciliation Commission President's Fund for reparations and rehabilitation of victims of gross human rights violations under the apartheid regime. 
Although President Mandela has been to Switzerland on various occasions, notably to attend the World Economic Forum in Davos in 1997 and to attend the 7th Annual World Telecommunications Forum and Exhibition in 1995, this is the first time that he will be visiting the country officially. 
ISSUED BY THE DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS PRETORIA 20 AUGUST 1997</body></text></speech>