<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1997-12-31">31 December 1997</date><text><term key="546" /><body>Good evening! 

Thobela! 

Ndiyanibulisa! 

Lochani 

Ke a le dumedisa! 

Ngiyanibingelela! 

Ri perile! 

Goeienaand! 

Ndi Madekwana! 

As 1997 draws to a close, South Africa faces a future filled with both challenge and hope. 

If the early years of our democracy brought celebration of our very freedom and common humanity; if these first three years of freedom meant the outpouring of national pride in the prowess of our sporting teams, in our new constitution and more; then this past year has been one in which slowly but surely, we are all coming to better appreciate the difficulties of change, as well as the sweat and toil required to improve our lives and forge our unity as a nation. 

At a time when some of the most vibrant economies in the world have been buffeted by storms, we have performed relatively well. This encourages us to join hands with a new determination – as a big and small business, as government and society at large - to create more jobs. 

We are proud that the numbers of people gaining access to basic services grow in thousands by the day. Water, electricity, sanitation and health-care have reached communities for whom they were but a dream. Our children now entering school will never know the painful burden of racial education. 

South Africans have never been so united in their determination to deal with crime. The syndicates are being uncovered and a life of crime is becoming more and more uncomfortable. Steadily, the holes in the criminal justice system are being plugged. For this modest achievement, law-abiding citizens and members of the security forces alike deserve our congratulations. 

While the Truth and Reconciliation Commission is taking us on a difficult journey, it is one that has helped us understand our painful past. Incomplete and imperfect as the process may be, it shall leave us less burdened by the past and unshackled to pursue a glorious future. 

Though we take rightful pride in these achievements, we know that they are only a start. We know that the number of people reached in service delivery are not nearly enough; the quality still needs much improvement; the crime rate is still too high; and the divisions of the past still play themselves out in many areas. We know that our tasks will take years to complete. 

For our country to succeed requires the combined efforts of all of us, in all walks of life. It requires all spheres of government, not least at local level, to fulfil the trust which citizens have placed in us. 

For us all, therefore, the new year must be one in which each and every one of us shares the responsibility for building on the foundation that has been laid. 

Our achievements so far have shown what can be done when we set aside petty differences and together pursue the common good. 

By working together we can build the South Africa of our dreams. 

I wish you all a happy, prosperous and fulfilling New Year. 

God bless South Africa.</body></text></speech>