<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1997-01-04">04 January 1997</date><text><term key="1339" /><body>Dominee 
Friends and Family 
Honoured Guests 
Ladies and Gentlemen 
Shaun and Juanita 
It is a great honour to be present here this afternoon, and to share in the joy of the occasion. 
Sport has not only brought so much joy to the people of our country. It has also played an incalculable part in bringing our previously divided society together, uniting us as one nation around a common national pride. 
To be able to share in this ceremony involving one of our most beloved national sporting stars, is therefore such a great pleasure and privilege for us. Marriage is n act of supreme unification between two people; and as you, Shaun, have helped unite our country through your sporting prowess, we now share in saluting this personal union of yours. 
Ons wil vir jou en Juanita vanmiddag alles van die beste toe-wens vir 'n lang en gelukkige samesyn. Mag die spanpoging wat julle twee vandag aanpak, net so suksesvol wees as die van daardie ander span waarvan jy lid is. 
We are wishing you and Juanita all the success that Bafana Bafana have achieved. We are confident that in the same manner as you have drawn succour and strength from your mutual support up till now, you will continue to do so in this new union into which you enter today. 
You represent a powerful role model to thousands of people in this country. Your success as a sporting star could only come through commitment, dedication and application. We have no doubt that you will approach this new venture and stage in your life with similar commitment. And that in that way you will bring the same exemplary role to this undertaking. 
We know that the two of you will be spending a considerable amount of your time together abroad. Again we are confident that you will continue to be the great ambassadors for your country as you have so consistently been up till now. And may you in those foreign parts - far way from friends and family- find in one another the warmth and support you will need. 
Shaun, Juanita, familie en vriende: dit is nogmaals ‘n groot eer om te kan deel in so ‘n vreugedevolle dag in die lewe van een van ons nasionale helde. Mag die lewe vorentoe julle twee met geluk en seeninge toebedeel. 
We all join- together with millions other who are not present here- to wish all the luck and joy in the years that lie ahead. 
Thank you.</body></text></speech>