Your Excellencies; 
Ministers; 
Ladies and Gentlemen, 
It is a great honour to have the task of chairing a meeting whose deliberations hold such consequences for the people of Zaire and for our whole continent of Africa. 
Although history is not defined by such moments alone, none of us present can fail to be impressed with the import of what transpires here today. 
Peace, stability and the entrenchment of democracy in Zaire are the right of the people of that great country. 
In a world increasingly defined by the interdependence of nations, they are of direct interest not only to Zaire's immediate neighbours, but to the entire African continent, and indeed to the world. 
Africa's rebirth has kept pace with our success in securing democratic governance, the protection of human rights and the peaceful resolution of conflicts. That renaissance would falter should stability elude a nation of Zaire's weight at the heart of our continent. Conversely, success would open the way for maximum benefits from co-operation between nations for growth and development. 
The consequences of success or failure touch us all - for none of us can prosper in isolation or enjoy security on our own; and none can succeed in addressing the urgent and basic needs of Africa's people. 
That is why the international community - the United Nations and the Organisation of African Unity in particular - have been so concerned to do whatever could be done to support and facilitate a process leading to Zairean peace talks. 
We would like to take this opportunity to express our appreciation of the work of Ambassador Sahnoun, Special Representative to the Great Lakes Region, in co-ordinating all the international efforts to facilitate a resolution of the situation in Zaire by Zaireans themselves. South Africa has been glad to play a small part in these efforts. 
We should also express our thanks to President Lissouba for the arrangements that made this meeting possible. 
Today's talks are the outcome of a Zairean process which the international community has been able to facilitate. 
In the course of that process the two parties converged upon the broad outline of a path towards peace and stability - negotiations to bring about a peaceful political solution of the conflict, necessitating a complete cease-fire; and a process of transition leading to transparent, fair and inclusive elections, as steps towards fundamental and democratic change. 
That consensus was the framework for the bold decision of the Zairean leaders that the time had come for them to meet in order to achieve these goals. 
Situations of conflict bring a special call on leaders. To them falls the task of creating the peaceful conditions which allow the good men and women who exist on each side of the conflict and in every community, to come forward and work together for the good of the whole nation. History judges us as leaders on how far we succeed in putting the interests of our country before anything else. 
Africa is filled with hope that today's talks between Zaire's leaders will lead towards a resolution of their country's crisis that is in the interests of all the people of Zaire; that African leaders are indeed finding a solution to an African problem.