<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1997-09-30">30 September 1997</date><text><term key="1449" /><body>Against the background of burgeoning bilateral relations between the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia and the Republic of South Africa and in response to an invitation by President Nelson Mandela, His Royal Highness Prince Sultan Bin Abdulaziz Second Deputy Prime Minister, Minister of Defence and Aviation Inspector General of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, undertook a visit to South Africa between the 24 and 29 of September 1997. His Royal Highness was warmly received by President Mandela and senior office bearers of his government. 
While in South Africa His Royal Highness Prince Sultan met with President Nelson Mandela and Deputy President Thabo Mbeki, as well as Mr Joe Modise, Minister of Defence, Mr Penuell Maduna, Minister of Mineral and Energy Affairs and other senior officials of the South African Government. These meetings were held in an atmosphere of cordiality and understanding resulting in constructive and fruitful discussions emphasising the friendly relations between both countries. 
Both sides indicated pleasure at the positive and fruitful direction of relations and expressed confidence in the leadership of the Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques, King Fahad Bin Abdulaziz Al-Saud King of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia and President Nelson Mandela of South Africa. 
His Royal Highness Prince Sultan Bin Abdulaziz welcomed the upcoming State Visit to the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia by the South African President Nelson Mandela, who accepted the invitation of the Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques. President Mandela expressed his gratitude to the Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques for the generous invitation and stated that he was looking forward to visiting the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. 
Both countries reiterated their mutual desire to enhance bilateral co-operation in various fields including encouraging and enhancing joint investments and efforts to increase trade between the two countries. The Kingdom of Saudi Arabia welcomed South Africa's desire to increase its petroleum imports from the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia and also welcomed the South African commitment to enhance mining exploration in the Kingdom. 
During discussions concerning regional and international issues the importance of enhancing the Middle East Peace Process was emphasised as a basis to achieve a permanent, just and comprehensive peace in the Middle East, founded upon relevant United Nations resolutions, the principles of the Madrid-conference and the principle of land for peace. 
Both sides called for all parties to the peace process to respect commitments and agreements already concluded and agreed that violations of the various accords will lead to threats to peace and security in the region. They also urged the two co-sponsors of the peace process to resume their important role in this context. 
The two countries reiterated that the legitimate rights of the Palestinian people and the preservation of the varied religious character of the Holy City of Jerusalem are key elements of the Peace Process and condemned attempts to change the demographic character of the city. The two sides also emphasised the need to refocus bilateral peace negotiations on the stalled Syrian and Lebanese negotiations and pointed out that efforts to achieve peace and stability in the region will also depend upon progress in this regard. 
They further reiterated the importance of full compliance by Iraq with all relevant Security Council resolutions relating to its' aggression against Kuwait, while at the same time expressing their joint commitment to the preservation of Iraq's unity and territorial integrity. 
Both sides emphasised their condemnation of terrorism in all it's forms and expressed the necessity for united action by the international community to fight those who are planning, financing, and implementing terrorism. 
His Royal Highness Prince Sultan Bin Abdulaziz expressed his thanks and appreciation for the kind reception and generous hospitality that he and his accompanying delegation were accorded by President Mandela and Deputy President Mbeki as well as other senior officials during his Royal Highness' visit to the Republic of South Africa, while President Mandela thanked his quests for undertaking this historic visit, which was the first by a senior Saudi delegation to South Africa. 
ISSUED BY THE DEPARTMENT OF FOREIGN AFFAIRS PRETORIA 30 SEPTEMBER 1997</body></text></speech>