Both President Nelson Mandela and Deputy President Thabo Mbeki are disgusted and horrified by the ludicrous allegations by some politicians that there are differences between them. 

They are concerned that there is a tendency among political parties to stoop to the lowest depths to further party political propaganda. 

Both President Mandela and Deputy President Mbeki would like to see a speedy resolution on the matters that have resulted in court action by the New National Party (NNP) and the Democratic Party (DP). 

They are of the view that a speedy resolution of these matters will enhance a positive atmosphere in preparations for the elections. Therefore the suggestion that there may be a difference of opinion either personal or political between the President and the Deputy President is nonsensical. 

The President and the Deputy President are disappointed that the leaders of the NNP and the DP have chosen to distort the contents of a confidential discussion between them and the President to suit their party political objectives. 

The President approached these leaders with the genuine desire to facilitate are solution of the contentious issues. In this, the President has the full support and backing of the Deputy President and when he referred the matters to the Deputy President and the legal advisors of the government, it was so that the process should be managed both expeditiously and efficiently. 

Both of them are now uncertain about the intentions of the New National Party and the Democratic Party in breaching this trust and therefore destroying the basis for any future discussions which might be aimed at resolving this problem. 

However, the President and the Deputy President will encourage the government's legal advisers to facilitate the discussions on the above matters in the hope that the leaders of the DP and NNP and other political organisations will realise the wisdom of raising national interest above narrow and petty party political interests. 

In the many decades of anti-apartheid resistance previous governments have attempted the tactic of sowing division within the liberation movement. This tactic has always failed. We are therefore concerned that when we thought our democracy was taking route, tactics that were used during our divisive past are being re-introduced. 

Both the President and the Deputy President are looking forward to an effective and politically abrasive election contest. They hope and pray that the opposition will play their part in enriching that contest instead of employing base and useless tactics which failed under apartheid