<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="1999-03-24">24 March 1999</date><text><term key="1541" /><body>The PRESIDENT OF THE REPUBLIC: Madam Speaker, Deputy President and hon members, I am sure you are as surprised as I have been that I should address the House instead of the Deputy President. He called upon me, approximately 30 minutes ago, to say that he was going to ask me to speak. As the House knows, he is my leader. He is the President of the ANC. [Applause.] Therefore, I cannot say no. 
It may also be, with the people's will that he is going to be my successor, and I have to cultivate my relations with him. [Laughter.] But every human being passes through this world but once. 
This means that one has to use the opportunities that are available to one, because, as a general rule, once one misses one's opportunities, they will never be available again. One has to set out clearly, one's aims and objectives and strive for them without worrying very much about detractors. 
The ANC has observed this principle throughout its history. In the early 1950s we called upon the people of South Africa- black and white to send in their demands, which they would like to have written in a people's charter. After that we invited the leaders of all political organisations in this country, including the NP and the Liberal Party, to come to a meeting where we would discuss the problems of our country and chart the way forward. That invitation was rejected outright by the NP. The Liberal Party first agreed, but as we were preparing for this conference, they pulled out. 
In 1955 we issued our basic policy document, the Freedom Charter, and proclaimed that South Africa belonged to all its people, black and white. [Applause.] In 1961 we did exactly the same when we called for a national convention, inviting all political parties in this country to sit down and sort out our problems amicably. That invitation was again rejected by all the political parties in the country, except the AN C. 
In 1994 the leaders of the ANC approached the Nationalist government and asked for a meeting between the ANC and the government. We posed the question: What is the point of slaughtering one another when we could sit down and sort out our problems? Eventually, as members know, the NP government and the ANC met and began negotiations. That is the record of the ANC - wanting to unite the country, wanting to forget about all the cruelty committed against innocent people and stretching out our hand of friendship to our enemy. Nobody can deny that this is the record of this organisation. 
The struggle to overthrow white supremacy in this country was fought by the liberation movements in varying degrees - by the ANC, the PAC and Azapo. Supported by the international community, we overthrew white supremacy using our own resources and our own friends. But the task of transforming the country into what it is now could not be done by the liberation movements alone. It required the collective efforts of all South Africans. All of us here are responsible for that peaceful transformation. That is one thing we should compliment ourselves for, because all of us transformed South Africa from a polecat of the world to a miracle. 
For example, one of the things that surprised me in my recent visit to five different countries, is that the South African media only concentrated on what the President said. They kept a total silence about what the heads of states and heads of governments in the countries that we visited were saying. 
They did not refer to what they said at all. Is it because sometimes our media can be very superficial in its reportage? Or is it because they deliberately did not want to place before South Africans the compliments which were paid by every one of those countries to the miracle that we performed? It was one of the most disappointing discoveries on my part when I got the press cuttings and realised that our media was absolutely silent on very important observations made by leaders of government in the countries I visited. (Interjections.] 
I regretted this because it would have encouraged all South Africans, black and white, to appreciate our rare achievement in confounding the prophets of doom and avoiding bloodshed. I would like all of us to remember this because the perception from the outside world is that we are one country that has shown the world how to solve what are perceived as intractable problems. That is what we have achieved. 
A few years ago white South Africans in particular were shy to say: We are South Africans. Today, as a result of this collective effort of all of us, once one says that one is a South African, whether black or white, Afrikaans or English speaking, the doors of the world become wide open for that person. (Applause.] That is what we have achieved. It may well be that not all of us are aware of the significance of this peaceful transformation in which South Africans are now working together to address their problems. We must also examine very carefully whether what we are doing is a reflection of what is happening in the country. I sometimes wonder if we are aware of that. 
Just to talk about Afrikaners, ever since I came out of jail I have gone to businesses, black and white, Afrikaans and English speaking, and told them that I wanted them to deliver services to our people in the countryside who did not have the facilities that we take for granted in the cities. I asked them to build clinics and schools. 
I have been doing this since 1990 when I came out of prison. Not one businessperson has ever said no. I have involved a large number of our people to take business to the countryside in order to build, to take these facilities to the people there. 
One remarkable case was when I asked business to raise R55 million so that I could build a centre in Newcastle for the children I had released from jail. They raised that amount within one week. (Applause.] We started with the big companies like Anglo American, Rembrandt, Liberty Life, Sanlam, Old Mutual and Barlows, and the rest followed. They raised R55 million within a week. 
Last year alone I took 30 businesspeople to different provinces to build schools and clinics. I have invited, for example, Shenge over there when I took Oppenheimer to a hospital in Northern KwaZulu-Natal, because I did not want to politicise this matter. That is why I invited Shenge to join me. I also invited him when I took Stocks &amp; Stocks to the Shembe Community. I invited him when I went to build a school in Msinga and when we built a clinic jointly with the health department in KwaZulu-Natal. 
These are the things that are happening, where Afrikaners and English-speaking people - black and white - are co-operating in delivering services. Are those members aware of these things? Are they aware of what educational institutions - both Afrikaans and English speaking - are doing in this country? 
Both the Deputy President and Chief Buthelezi have outlined their discussions with universities. They have done far more than has been reported by our two leaders here. Hon members should take a university like RAU which has established special schools for gifted black children which they are financing, apart from the black students that they have admitted in their university. Are those members aware of what both Afrikaans and English-speaking churches are doing? 
This negativism which emerges in every discussion here, is not actually seen out there. The overwhelming majority of South Africans, black and white, see this rainbow nation emerging. They appreciate the difficulties, but they know that in the 350 years of the presence of whites in this country, no government has ever delivered the services which this Government has delivered to our people. (Applause.] This has not happened before. We went out of our way to see that it does. I think examples of oppressed people who go to their oppressor to ask them to sit down and talk are few and far between. We had that courage to go to them and say: Let us sit down and talk. We are building national unity. We are promoting the spirit of reconciliation, and yet there are some people in this country who are using the ANC as a target for the most vicious attacks. They want to place before the country and the world all that is negative. We know that there are problems. If one considers that all of us, unlike them, never had the opportunity of being trained in governance, one will realise how well we are doing. They belong to families which had high standards of education. 
We, without any experience whatsoever, having being denied the opportunities to get an education, were able to run this advanced country. We were able to bring about peace to liberate everybody - the oppressed and the oppressor. I would at least have expected solid support, especially from the people on the other side, because the opportunities ... (Interjections] [Applause] ... they had of going to school and acquiring knowledge are needed. We want them to be like Derek Hanekom and Alec Erwin. (Laughter.] (Applause.] Listen to me. 
These are men - including the young lady over there, Gill Marcus - who sit in Government, whether they like it or not, and help decide the future of this country, their future. (Laughter.] (Applause.] We want them to be part of the majority, absolutely. I am not saying that they should join the AN C. (Laughter.] However, if they join the ANC I will not fight them. (Laughter.] 
What I am saying is that we want them to be part of the majority because of their skills and training. They will, like Derek Hanekom, Alec Erwin and Gill Marcus, be able to take up positions of leadership, not because of their colour, but because of their training and skills. That is what South Africa wants, and what the other sections of our community, that is business, the churches and the educational institutions, are doing today. 
This is a great country with great leaders. Even when they differ with us and come to us with their criticisms, one can see that these are intelligent men talking. Every time Mr Van Schalkwyk and Tony Leon speak, even when I disagree with what they say, I can see that they have the skills that are wanted by any country. All that is needed . . . (Laughter.] All that is needed is for us to try to be part of this rainbow nation, not by what we say, but by the way we look at problems. 
When there are problems, they should go to the Deputy President and say that they do not understand this and that. They should ask him to consider any aspect even before they come to Parliament, for they are entitled to that. As leaders there are accepted ways of addressing problems, so that the masses are not confused and divided. 
I am very proud of all our parliamentarians, because they are doing a remarkable job. As far as I am concerned, I will still have my considered address to Parliament on Friday. For now, I am carrying out the orders of my leader, who said that I should speak in his place. I am very happy that members listened to me, and I wish them the best of luck and a very enjoyable election campaign. [Laughter.] (Applause.</body></text></speech>