<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="2000-07-12">12 July 2000</date><text><term key="1203" /><body>It was my great privilege to be asked to 
address a conference on financial 
services, arranged by INVESTEC in 
London, two weeks ago. I then indicated 
to the invited guests there what an 
honour it was for a poor unemployed old 
man to rub shoulders with such 
luminaries of the financial world. 
Little would I have known that in less 
than a month INVESTEC would add 
further to my elevation to these 
esteemed ranks of the captains of 
finance. 
I need therefore not explain to you how 
honoured I am to put in yet another 
appearance at an occasion like this. 
At the same time it relieves me of the 
necessity to explain to this gathering 
why it would be inappropriate for me to 
try and repeat the address I gave to that 
gathering in London two weeks ago - a 
gathering that focussed on South Africa 
and included a large number of South 
Africans, many of whom I suspect will 
again be present here today. 
I may just be allowed to repeat in a 
modified way my comments about the 
soundness of our macro-economic 
fundamentals, and particularly of the 
contribution of our financial sector in 
that regard. 
In London I obviously had to make those 
comments by way of commending our 
country to potential foreign investors. 
Today I can make those comments as a 
gesture of appreciation to the financial 
services 
sector of our economy for the way that 
they have made of that economy the 
robust one it is. The manner in which we 
survived the impact and trauma of the 
Asian crisis is in no small manner clue to 
the soundness of our banking and 
financial services sector. 
The effects of the Asian crisis reminded 
us like few other occurrences of the last 
years that we are, for better or for worse, 
one inter-dependent world. What 
happened in one corner of the world had 
major effects on people all over the 
globe. And once more it was proved that 
the vulnerable and the poor were most 
hard hit by such global tremors. 
In London I pleaded for a new global 
sensitivity for the importance of equity in 
international relations. It is becoming 
increasingly clear that the free flow of 
capital and finance is not always serving 
such objectives of equity. The movement 
of money is often not directed by social 
purposes, but rather by the 
considerations of short term profits. 
Here at home today, I must cast those 
same pleas in domestic terms. The 
financial institutions in our country, like 
all other agencies of our economy, 
should have it as conscious goal of their 
operations to serve equity. Too often we 
still find that those traditionally excluded 
from the fruits of our progress continue 
to be marginalised. 
The development of small, medium and 
micro enterprises is generally 
recognised to be crucial to job creation 
in our country. Long term stability also 
in our political system is dependent on 
the success of black economic 
empowerment through which all South 
Africans will feel that they have a stake 
in the economy. 
Too often we hear the lament from the 
small entrepreneurs that their 
contribution to economic development 
and job creation is being stifled by their 
lack of access to financing. Similarly, 
one hears the comment that black 
economic empowerment is being 
impeded by the absence of financing, 
and the growing reluctance of the 
financial sector - which is still 
traditionally dominated and controlled — 
to continue investment in empowerment. 
If charity begins at home, here is an 
opportunity for us to demonstrate that 
domestic solidarity. If we can harness 
our domestic energies towards equity, 
we shall stand so much stronger as 
members of the developing world to 
argue for equity goals in global affairs. 
But, as I have indicated in the beginning, 
I am not here to repeat myself or to make 
a lengthy speech. Suffice for me to 
congratulate once more the financial 
sector of our economy and to commend 
to them even greater effort towards 
making our society one in which all 
people will indeed feel that democratic 
change had made a difference to their 
daily lives. 
I thank you and I wish you well.</body></text></speech>