Distinguished guests and friends: I am afraid that I must repeat a remark which I made twice since I arrived in this country. I have no illusions why so many of you are here. You want to see what an unemployed pensioner looks like. Some of you who are observant will notice that I am shaking behind my trousers. It is not usual for me to address such a distinguished crowd. I hope that you will bear with me if, in the course of my address, I stumble because of the fear that has seized me. 

It is a privilege for me to celebrate with you this extension of the British Museum, an institution about which I had heard so much as a young man. This institution, with its extraordinary collection, has a fascination and message for people far outside the borders of Britain. It represents a bringing together of works of art from all across the world, thus representing an image of the manner in which people have influenced and interacted with each other, over the centuries. The collection in this institution provides an opportunity for people to gain a greater understanding of each other’s culture, and to have a sense of the continuous history of world civilisation. 

I am particularly proud that the museum is about to open three new African galleries that will give full credit to the contribution that Africa has made to world art. They will show the influence that African art and artefacts have exerted on European artists, particularly in the last century. They will be a reminder that Africa has not only learned much artistically from other continents; it has also significantly contributed its own values and creativity. 

Reciprocal exchange and mutual influence among people from across the globe have a long history, as this collection reminds us. This global interaction has become much more rapid and widespread over the last few decades, as the amazing developments in communications and information technology have brought the world so much closer together. One consequence is that ideas, styles and ways of thinking can connect with each other more easily and quickly. 

A feature of our contemporary world is the global market created by business and commerce. In this global market, our interdependence has increased and deepened dramatically. This speeding up of world communications is equally important in the fields of art and politics. New ideas and concepts can race across the world almost as quickly and casually as money and goods, interacting with the ideas of other people, often with far reaching consequences few people notice at the time. 

This cross pollination of ideas and concepts played an important role in our struggle against apartheid in South Africa. The struggle was led by the liberation movements, and eventually successfully concluded through the participation of all South Africans, who sought the path of peaceful negotiations rather than destructive civil war. However much pride South Africans take from having resolved the conflict on their own, we recognise and acknowledge the crucial role played by international support and solidarity. The great schools of emancipatory thought from other parts of the world fundamentally influenced the concepts and ideas that directed our struggle. 

Our fight against apartheid was for national liberation, at the same time as it was about the integration of our country and its people into the wider world of thought, culture, arts, trade and commerce. We remain indebted to the support that we gained from across the world, not only from our political allies, but also from performers, artists and writers, who saw apartheid as an outrage against the whole concept of cultural freedom and exchange. 

The sense of solidarity and support from the world’s cultures added to our confidence about the political negotiations South Africans entered into at the start of the nineties. We knew that the exclusiveness that apartheid had deliberately fostered could be reversed, to produce a country where there was room for everyone and respect for one another’s cultures and traditions. We knew that we could learn much from other countries that had their own history and experiences of tolerance, co existence and mutual enrichment. 

We were convinced that South Africa could bring something to the world through reconciliation and a joint effort of reconstruction, after our history of division and discrimination. We had faith that our insistence on a common humanity also had relevance to other countries. 

This reciprocal learning is one of the great benefits of the globalisation of our contemporary world. The globalised nature of our world was one of the great new features that my colleagues and I had to catch up with at the end of 27 years sojourn on Robben Island, and other prisons. 

Incidentally, my secretary says to me every day, "You have been loafing for 27 years. You must now work and be busy every day." So, if you see me here today and in California tomorrow, you must know who the culprit is. 

I say that we had faith that our insistence on a common humanity also had relevance to other countries. 

The world had become much smaller, as I realised when racing on jumbo jets that I had never seen before, and talked every day on amazing new international telephones. I had to acquaint myself with this new phenomenon of globalisation, that enabled money and capital to flow instantly across the globe, and made the economies of the world startlingly more interdependent. 

The effects and consequences of globalisation had to be internalised by many other South Africans, as well. South Africa became isolated from the international community during the apartheid years, and now saw how closely interconnected countries and economies had become. We welcome the process of globalisation. It is inescapable and irreversible. We can no more ignore it, as I said before, that we can reject the idea of winter by refusing to wear warm clothes. It can carry with it not only investment and transfer of expertise, but also knowledge and understanding of other people and cultures. 

But if globalisation is to create real peace and stability across the world, it must be a process benefiting all. It must not allow the most economically and politically powerful countries to dominate and submerge the countries of the weaker and peripheral regions. It should not be allowed to drain the wealth of smaller countries towards the smaller ones, or to increase the inequality between richer and poorer regions. 

Equally important, the local and regional cultures must not be submerged and overwhelmed by the cultures of the richer countries, whether in art, film, music, or literature. Any healthy and vibrant marketplace consists of a fair exchange amongst a variety of goals. The fair exchange of the diversity of cultures is still important as the lifeblood of civilisation. African people are confident that they have contributed much to the world, and will continue to do so. 

There is concern, though, that the playing field of cultural exchange is becoming lop sided, and that local artists and creators are finding it hard to make themselves seen and heard in the ruthless intensity of global competition. A peaceful and civilised world will always depend upon a balance between global organisation and communication on one hand, and healthy local traditions and dignity on the other, with each representing and cross fertilising the other. 

In every continent, all through history, the great artistic achievements have depended on reaching out to other cultures, and learning from them. That is why I take special pride in being invited here to the British Museum, where the world’s art and artefacts are displayed all around us, each having played its part in enriching and cross fertilising the world’s civilisations. 

This great museum may have begun as the beneficiary of British imperial power, but it has become a truly international institution, supported by global donors. It attracts scholars and tourists from across the world to its unique collection of artistic treasures, in which every continent is represented. And that is why I am also delighted that this occasion and this lecture theatre are sponsored by British Petroleum. For, this company has itself developed into being a genuinely multinational corporation. It includes managers and employees from every continent and almost every background, who can constantly learn from each other. 

I came out of jail in 1990, and made it a point to take the private sector, black and white, Afrikaans and English speaking to the countryside, to build schools, clinics and community centres where such facilities have never been known. One of the countries that is in the forefront in this regard is BP. Therefore, it is a great honour for me to participate in an occasion that is sponsored by them. The sense of balance, mutual respect and sensitivity for the other is key to any successful global organisation. It is also key to the maintenance of world peace. 

We in South Africa, for so long separated and divided by racial conflict, have learned that our safety and prosperity depend on breaking through divisions and realising that our well being is indivisible. So, too, is world peace. This museum reminds us of that, and inspires us towards that goal. 

I will end by telling an anecdote that I have related several times, especially when I address such august gatherings. I also told it this morning, in this country. 

A four year old young lady came to my gate, and security told me that there was a young lady at my gate to see me. I said, please open the gate, and let her come in. They said, but Mr President, she is arrogant and cheeky. I replied, precisely for that reason, let her come in. She came through the gate, and I was sitting in my lounge. She did not knock. She just stormed in, and then asked me the question: 

"How old are you?" 

Well, I said, I don’t know, but I was born long, long ago. She said,"Two years ago?" 

I said, No, much longer than that. Then she suddenly changed subject, and said, "Why did you go to jail?" 

I replied that I did not go to jail because I liked, but some people sent me there. She asked, who? I said it was people who did not liked me. She asked, "How long did you stay there?" 

Again, the "two years" came up and, again, I pointed out that I cannot remember how long I was there, but that it was a long time. Then, she made this devastating observation: 

"You must be a foolish old man." 

Well, ladies and gentlemen: if you feel that my remarks this evening have not lived up to expectations, please, I implore you, just be a little more diplomatic than that young lady. 

I thank you