We in the African National Congress are 
heirs of brave African men and women that 
fought for National Liberation for over three 
generations. The post Second World War 
leaders Dr Xuma, Dr Moroka, Chief Albert 
Luthuli and Oliver Tambo made the ANC, 
the vanguard of the struggle in defeating the 
apartheid regime in 1994. We in the ANC 
did not do this alone. We were with the 
South African Indian Congress under the 
able leadership of Drs Yusuf Dadoo and 
Monty Naicker, and with the Coloured 
Peoples Congress led by Rahim, and the 
Congress of Democrats led by Bram 
Fischer. The UDF and the hundreds of its affiliated organizations, the trade union 
movement, the Communist Party, the 
Churches, the women and other freedom 
loving people. The ANC is worthy of praise 
for tenaciously striving by various means for 
so long, culminating in the Freedom Charter 
in 1955, the first democratic elections of 
1994 and the second election in 1999 in 
both of which the people of South Africa 
entrusted their future to us. The vast 
majority of the people of South Africa voted 
for the ANC because of its record of 
struggle since 1912. 
Thabo Mbeki, Cyril Ramaphosa, Joe Slovo 
and other leaders piloted through the 
Constituent Assembly a constitution of 
which we together with many of the nations 
of the world are proud. The ANC 
government has made considerable 
advances in relation to housing, health, 
education and social services. 
The ANC's successes have not been as a 
result of the efforts of any particular 
individual but rather due to the concerted 
effort of the ANC's collective leadership. 
Our national executive, democratically 
elected, consists of women and men of all 
colours, from various provinces, speaking 
many languages, of different religious 
beliefs, different levels of education, 
different occupations and mainly from 
disadvantaged backgrounds. The same 
applies to the ANC's elected 
representatives in Parliament in the 
Provincial Legislatures and in Local 
Government. They are each in his or her 
way the leading figures in our organization 
and government. 
The unity of purpose of those who served 
the ANC has created a legacy amongst us 
of collective leadership. Let us remember 
that despite oppression, despite hangings, 
bannings, imprisonments and exile, our 
Liberation Movement remained united like 
no other in the world. Oliver Tambo, Alfred 
Nzo, Thabo Mbeki, Joe Slovo, Chris Hani 
and many others acting as a collective 
leadership in exile and despite great 
difficulties keeping in touch with those in 
South Africa, including us behind bars on 
Robben Island and elsewhere, held fast. 
The prophecies of our opponents that race, 
tribalism, ideological and other differences 
would drive us in different directions did not 
come to pass. The collective leadership 
enjoyed the loyalty and respect of practically 
all who have embraced the struggle for 
liberation. 
Similarly elements in the opposition parties 
suffer from similar delusions. They nick- 
pick on various alleged contradictions in 
statements made by ANC leaders, praise 
some and condemn others with the hope of 
creating dissent. We assure them that their 
efforts will not bear the fruit they desire. 
The need for collective leadership is as 
necessary now as it has been in the past. 
We need the commitment of leaders at all 
levels in order to achieve the better life for 
all that we promised our people. We need 
not be ashamed in admitting that poverty is 
still with us. It is not enough to say that we 
have inherited it, it is more important to take 
steps as a matter of the utmost urgency to 
put an end to it. We do not need careerists 
or opportunists in the various levels of 
government. I agree fully with President 
Thabo Mbeki in his condemnation of such 
people. We must encourage those who 
consider themselves as members of 
minority groups to join us in our efforts to 
transform our society by putting to an end 
the vast differences between the poor vast 
majority and the very small but very rich 
minority. We should urge those who 
criticize us to take positive steps to solve 
our problems, support our courts and 
administration of justice, our security forces, 
the structures established for the avoidance 
of conflict and show some optimism in 
relation to the future of our country rather 
than being prophets of doom, that adversely 
affect would be investors in our economic 
future. 
It is not necessary for me to chalk up our 
successes. They are well known even to 
those who make odious comparisons 
between us and some of our neighbours and 
other African countries that are experiencing 
grave political and economical difficulties. 
I withdrew from my leadership positions in 
the African National Congress and the 
government. As I said upon my release 
from prison I am and will remain a loyal and 
disciplined member of the African National 
Congress. I have confidence in our 
President, our collective leadership and the 
good judgment of the vast majority of our 
members and indeed the vast majority of 
the people of South Africa. I have full 
confidence in our collective leadership. But, 
this does not mean that there may not be 
differences of opinion and even 
disappointments amongst us. If there are 
they must be debated fully but let everyone 
accept the decision of the majority and work 
hard to implement it. As for criticism from 
outside our ranks let us be tolerant though 
often we are not told what they would have 
done if they were in our position. Our letters 
of confidence and the good judgment of the 
vast majority of the people in South Africa 
they know that despite our failures real or 
imagined nobody could have done better 
than us in the comparatively short period 
that we have been in power. Nor has any 
workable plans shown how to do better in 
the future. 
I have spoken about collective leadership.