<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="2001-04-01">01 April 2001</date><text><term key="1091" /><body>While I am not in a position to personally attend the opening of this important venture, I want to express my appreciation for having been invited. 

Through this message I wish to congratulate London Clubs International on what I have no doubt is a very wise decision, viz. to invest in this manner in South Africa. 

I deliberately say congratulate rather than merely thanking you. Obviously, we need at the same time to express our thanks and gratitude for such investments. 

Such investments should, however, be mutually beneficial and not in the nature of aid to the investment recipient. And I can assure you that South Africa, and particularly the sector you have chosen to invest in, is an investment that will yield returns to make your venture fruitful. 

South Africa, on the other hand, needs foreign investment for its economy to grow, flourish and provide opportunities for all its people. 

The tourism industry had been identified as one of the key sectors for economic growth with job creation. Your particular investment decision is, therefore, wise and strategic and of crucial importance to our economy. 

The geographic area, too, is of particular significance. The Vaal Triangle holds a particular position of fame in the gallery of resistance history in this country. The sacrifices and heroism of the people of this area deserve to be recognised and acknowledged through the social and economic benefits that flow from development after our democratic changes. Your investment significantly contributes to that. 

I am particularly happy to learn that the economic investment is accompanied by other social projects such as, for example, involvement in the Sharpeville museum. 

That you are going into this venture with significant participation of empowerment partners further adds to the long-term social value of your undertaking. 

It is my great pleasure to have been able to participate in your opening through this medium. 

May it go well with your venture, yielding profits and growth that will be to the benefit and the creation of a better life for all. 

I thank you</body></text></speech>