We are a young nation. We face many challenges as we set out to compete in the modern globalised world. 
We have overcome great political challenges, astounding the world with our innovativeness and our capacity to find solutions for seemingly intractable political problems. 
The national energy that drove us then was surely not a one-off accident. It came from deep within our accumulated and stored up national potential. 
We have seen much evidence over the last few years of that energy being expressed in other areas of our national life. We have witnessed the genius of our young nation being given free reign. 
The story of young Mark Shuttleworth is a sterling example in that regard. His spirit of enterprise, hard work, self-reliance and caring for those with whom he worked inspired all of us. 
He exemplifies the resolve and the potential of our young nation. 
The launch of the Shuttleworth Foundation stands similarly in that spirit. 
Our young nation cannot start to compete successfully in the modern world unless we provide to our youth education and training of the highest quality. 
The resource of our century is knowledge. 
Our country and our continent will be emancipated to the extent that we move ourselves to the cutting-edge frontiers of modern age knowledge. 
We know that this is possible. 
Talks of an African reawakening are predicated on the faith that we can through our own efforts, in partnership with others in the world, educate the people of our country and continent to fully share in the knowledge treasures of humanity. 
Nothing of worth comes easily. It always asks for hard work and, particularly in our modern world, innovation. 
This is true particularly in the field of education and training. We suffer a tremendous backlog because of the legacy of our past. The resource constraints that we face - materially and in terms of human capacity - are equally daunting. 
We are now again called upon to delve deeply into that national potential. 
The vision and mission of the Shuttleworth Foundation testify to the depth of that potential. 
The spirit of enterprise that caused a young man to reach the top echelons in a highly competitive world industry, is now put to the service of education in our country. 
I want to congratulate, commend and thank the Shuttleworth Foundation for their decision to embark on this project in this very crucial area. 
The future of our nation truly depends upon the success you, and those in partnership with you, achieve in this field. 
I wish you well.