<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="2002-11-02">02 November 2002</date><text><term key="1575" /><body>I want to pay a sincere personal tribute to Diana, Princess of Wales and especially to her humanitarian work. She highlighted neglected causes. She reached out to people on the margins of society. She made even the most humble people feel special. Princess Diana took positive advantage of her celebrity status and used this to challenge and fight stigma attached to poverty, to people with terminal diseases especially those with HIV/AIDS. It was the Princess who uttered gently words to the effect that touching, kissing and holding a person with HIV/AIDS cannot make a person infected. When she stroked the limbs of someone with leprosy, or sat on the bed of a man with H1V/AIDS and held his hand, she transformed public attitudes and improved the life chances of such people. Her love for children went beyond the European borders and boundaries. 
The world saw her challenging world powers and attacking African leaders on the issues of wars and landmines, whose number one victims remained innocent children. 
As we gather here today, I urge everyone present and the world large to learn from her example and embrace her legacy. As we celebrate her life let us all be inspired to continue to change the lives of the less fortunate both now 
and in the future. Ladies and gentleman the coming together of the Nelson Mandela Children's Fund and the Diana Princess of Wales Memorial Fund will indeed benefit children distressed by HIV/AIDS. It gives me great pleasure to announce a joint programme of work which will build on strengths and synergies 
between the two organisations in the area of HIV/AIDS. 
AIDS is our number one enemy. This enemy can be defeated. While the research for a cure continues, four principles: love, support, acceptance and care for those affected can make us winners. 
The Nelson Mandela Children's Fund is on a crusade to provide opportunities for children who are orphaned by HIV/AIDS and those whose parents are living with HIV/AIDS. The Fund attempts to keep the dreams of childhood and aspiration of youth alive. The Fund promotes positive living among those with HIV/AIDS. Relationships with organisations such as the Diana Princess of Wales Memorial Fund will ensure that human dignity is not compromised by the natural process of living with a terminal illness and will provide us the space to create positive experience for affected children. This of course, ensures that children grow up to appreciate the legacy of their parents. The two organisations will continue their work to improve care and support for people who are living with HIV/AIDS, restore human dignity and compassion to the cultural process of dying, support children orphaned as a result of HIV/AIDS and give hope to families and children affected by HIV/AIDS in the poorest parts of South Africa. 
Caring for people who are dying and helping the bereaved was something for which Princess Diana had passion and commitment. But this remains a neglected field in many governments. In South Africa however, I am encouraged by the latest policy on Social Development which focuses Government and business involvement on the needs of families coping with terminal illness particularly HIV/AIDS. 
This environment will enable this new partnership between the Nelson Mandela Children's Fund and the Diana Princess of Wales Memorial Fund to flourish and provide lessons for good practice. The international response to HIV/AIDS 
overlooks palliative care, which allows for people to die with dignity but more importantly it overlooks the need to support families after bereavement. 
The South African Government estimates that a total of 4.7 million (10% of its population) are infected with the virus. At the receiving end of suffering are children with more than 660 000 having been orphaned by the pandemic. In addition 250 000 children live with HIV/AIDS. 
The Nelson Mandela Children's Fund work with such children has shown incredible results. In one such programme, the quality of life of HIV/AIDS children improved significantly after appropriate interventions. The Salvation Army's Carl Sithole Centre in Soweto, a project supported by the Fund gives emotional, physical and spiritual care and support to infected and 
affected children by HIV/AIDS. 
The Nelson Mandela Children's Fund has a R43 million (approximately £2.7 million) programme which we have named Goelama (a Tswana word meaning to care and nurture), this is our strategy to respond and mitigate the needs of children and families affected by H IV/AI DS. The programme reaches an estimated population of 1.5 million and has thus far reached at least 500 000 children directly affected by HIV/AIDS. 
I am honoured today to be announcing a joint programme of work between the Nelson Mandela Children's Fund and the Diana Princess of Wales Memorial Fund, I am convinced that this partnership will provide us with the most interesting models of care, support, development impact and sustainability. We shall be especially concerned with children orphaned by HIV/AIDS, those affected, those whose parents are dying and those living with HIV/AIDS.</body></text></speech>