<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<speech><date when="2002-09-07">07 September 2002</date><text><term key="1533" /><body>Your Excellency Ambassador Kurt Spallinger of Austria 

Distinguished guests 

Ladies and Gentlemen 

Members of the media, 

welcome to you all 

The establishment of the Children's Fund had humble beginnings through the committing of a third of my salary toward 

the setting of the Fund. Today the fund has collected a total of R299 million, of which 8197 million is set aside to ensure 

that the Fund lives beyond today's generation. 

This unprecedented achievement for a South African indigenous foundation could not have been a reality without the generous support of men and women like yourselves, who responded to my call to help grow the Fund. 

These individuals used their personal resources as well as their social standing to contribute substantial amounts to the Children's Fund. 

Tonight I wish to take this opportunity of welcoming new members to this family of generous contributors. These are former President's Club members who originally contributed R750 000 to equal my salary whilst serving as State President. They have chosen to double their contribution to the value of R1.5 million. 

I have pleasure of recognising Anant Singh as a Lifetime Founder member whose association with the Fund dates back from 1995 when he became one of the first President's Club Members. He introduced us to Teddy Forstman who became the first donor to donate US$1 million to the Fund. Recently Anant brought Will Smith to South Africa for the premiering of the 

movie, ALI, and he organised an auction the proceeds of which saw the Children's Fund receiving a donation of R1.5 million. 

I have pleasure to recognise another Lifetime Member, the Federal Republic of Austria, represented by Ambassador Kurt 

Spallinger. The Austrian government first joined as President's Club Members in 1995, we are glad that they remain loyal 

supporters of the Fund. 

My co-chair, Judge Dikgang Moseneke will also award certificates to new President's Club and Goodwill Ambassador Members to Europcar and Fli-Afrika respectively. 

I also wish to recognise our new partners who are providing direct support to our programmes, The Diana, Princess of Wales Memorial Fund, Special Olympics International and the Global Vision Magazine. 

I would like to extend my heart-felt gratitude to all our supporters be they individuals, institutions, organisations and governments who have contributed without fail to the Nelson Mandela Children's Fund. 

Your contribution has helped sustain the Fund and I once more encourage you to continue supporting the fund in its efforts 

to not only meet the needs of children today but to be able to do so for future generations equally. 

Today the Fund has seven offices operating in the United States of America, Spain, France, Netherlands, Canada, United Kingdom and Australia, most of whom are anchored volunteers contributing to the fundraising efforts of the fund in foreign lands. 

Present here tonight I call upon representatives from NMCF-Canada, NMCF-UK, and NMCF-Netherlands to rise for all of us to recognise them. Today the Fund has seven offices operating in the United States of America, Spain, France, Netherlands, Canada, United Kingdom and Australia, most of whom are anchored volunteers contributing to the fundraising efforts of the fund in foreign lands.</body></text></speech>