When we addressed the British House of Parliament in 1996 we referred to the symbolic closing of a circle of history that brought the destinies of our two countries together - first through colonisation and then through a genuine partnership as equals after our attainment of democracy and true sovereignty in 1994. 
Britain is one of our major partners in the international world today and part reason for that is to be found in the historic ties that developed between us even during those colonial days. Today we see Britain and Prime Minister Blair as one of the main champions of the New Partnership for African Development, so ably conceived and co-led by our own President. 
The launch of the Mandela-Rhodes initiative today is the closing of another circle within that larger historical circle. That it is being launched here at Groote Schuur, the home built for Cecil John Rhodes, holds a certain poignancy. Today this building serves the government of the new democratic South Africa. 
Cecil John Rhodes was a dominant figure in colonial society at the end of the 19th century. The last decade of the 20th century was marked by the attainment of democracy and the end of apartheid, one of the last expressions of the colonial experience in Africa. By combining our name to that of Cecil John Rhodes in this initiative is to signal a closing of that circle and a coming together of two strands in our history as we move forward to build a better life. 
The new Foundation will be based on a full and equal partnership between the Rhodes Trust and the Nelson Mandela Foundation acting on our behalf. It will seek to give full expression to the idea of partnership, fully in line with the spirit and intention of the New Partnership for African Development. 
The new Foundation will be another vehicle for providing opportunities in our larger efforts to build a world where peace and social justice will prevail. Poverty, illiteracy, preventable ill health, homelessness and other forms of social deprivation represent threats to our common future. We need to address these in partnerships that reach across historic and other divides. This initiative represents one such partnership. 
We are confident that this initiative will contribute to the much-needed development of our country and continent. We thank the Rhodes Trust for joining us in this partnership. And look forward to a long and fruitful life for this new entity. 
Thank you.