Friends, 
Thank you yet again for allowing me to address you at this press conference even though I have been told explicitly to retire from public life. But, I am concerned that not enough has been done by the public in general since the last four double six six four concert in Cape Town and that is why I am here today. We called on the public to act and although people responded from all over the world, we know that more can be done in South Africa, Ultimately the onus rests on the South African public to take responsibility for their own future. 
In 2003 we emphasized the plight of those infected and affected by Aids. UNAIDS recently reported that young women are six times more likely to be infected by the virus in comparison to men. Six times more! We are therefore calling on society more than ever before, to protect our young women and girls, Our future depends on them and we and the world must recognise our responsibility to them. We must mobilise to act and act soon before it is too late. 
There is another opportunity for the South African public and especially local music fans, to show their commitment to our country's future. On the 19th of March I will be at Fancourt to join a host of musicians; local and international, who are pulling together to address the HIV/Aids crises. 
I am pleased to announce that one of our newest four double six six four ambassadors, Will Smith, will be joining us at the concert and has agreed to be Master of Ceremonies. Will Smith will be introducing world-famous artists including Queen collaborating with Paul Rogers for the first time, Annie Lennox, Katie Melua, India Arie and Usher. Equally important he will introduce the performances of our local talent such as Johnny Clegg, Danny K and Mandoza, Karen Zoid, Prime Circle, Black Sunshine, Art Matthews, Mafikizolo, Mel Botes and Kabelo. 
Tickets are on sale now at Computicket. I want each and every South African that is serious about our country's future, to buy a ticket before it is too late. Apart from buying your ticket you can also pledge your personal support by sending a sms with your name to four double six six four.